[MUSIC]
［音乐］
Stanford University.
斯坦福大学
>> Okay well, welcome to lecture six of
欢迎来到第六课
Stanford CS193P winter of 2015.
2015冬季学期，斯坦福大学CS193P课程。
So today I am gonna do a little bit of
今天我们将要做一点点
demo action right at the beginning.
demo 在最开始的时候
I wanna show you a kind of a cool trick that you can do
我将会向你展示一种很酷的技巧
inside your storyboard, and we also, last time,
你可以在你的Storyboard里使用，我们同样的，在上次
didn't get to the point where we had actually a model for
没有为我们的MVC创建一个实际的 model
our MVC, our happiness MVC.
我们的 Happiness MVC
We had worked on the face view and got that working but
我们在 face view上工作过并且已经开始工作了
we didn't have a model,
我们没有一个 model
so I'm gonna just put that model in there, but then I am
所以我准备在这里放置一个 model，但是随后
going to jump right back into the slides and I am going to
我准备跳回进入 slides并且我准备
cover a very important concept, which is delegation.
掩盖一个重要的概念，就是 delegation
And I'll have to kinda go over Swift's protocol syntax, and
我很乐意去复习 Swift语言的 协议语法
then I will do a demo to show you how delegation works,
随后我将会制作一个demo用来向你们展示 delegation是怎么工作的
then I'm gonna cover gestures, okay?
随后我准备覆盖一些手势，明白？
We know how to draw in our view now from last time.
在上节课中我们知道了怎么在我们的 view中进行绘制
So, now we're gonna then talk about how we handle gestures.
所以，现在我们准备去探讨怎么样去处理手势
Pinches and pans and swipes and things like that.
类似于捏合、滑动或者类似的动作
And I think that'll probably use all of my time up.
我想这会在我所有的时间内使用的
But if I have a little bit of time at the end,
但是如果我在结束前有一点时间的话
I'm gonna get started on the next major topic.
我准备开始下一个主要的话题
Which we're gonna spend most of Wednesday on.
我们准备在周三进行探讨的
Which is multiple MVCs, right?
就是 multiple MVCs，明白？
We know how to build an MVC.
我们知道如何去创建一个 MVC
It's got a controller, it's got a model, it's got a view.
它有一个 controller，model，view
And now we're gonna build a bigger application by
然后我们将要创建一个大一点的应用
combining MVCs, okay?
通过结合多个 MVC，明白？
And that's critical, obviously,
并且那是很关键的，很明显
to growing the capability of size of app you can build.
增加功能会使你创建的APP的尺寸增加
So I'll try and fit in five or ten minutes of slides for
所以我将会尝试在5到10分钟内进行适配
that just to make sure we have more time on Wednesday.
以确保我们再周三的时候会有更多的时间
Anybody have any questions about any of this?
有人对这部分内容有问题么？
All right.
好吧
So, let's dive into this demo first, before I talk about.
所以，让我们先潜入这个demo，在我谈论这个之前
That, okay I am just going to bring up
那个，我只是准备造就
happiness from where we left off last time.
happiness 从我们上次离开的地方
And really all we had done here was the Face View,
然后我们在这里已经完成的是 Face View
we had not done our Happiness View.
我们没有完成我们的 Happiness View
In fact, if I switch over to our Happiness View controller,
事实上，如果我切换到我们的 Happiness View controller
you can see it is completely empty.
你可以看到它完全是空的
So one thing we're gonna do is
我们我们将要做的一件事是
fix our model here but before we do that I'm gonna show you
修复我们的 model在我准备向你们展示
something really cool that you can do in story boards.
一些你可以在storyboards里完成的很酷的事之前
So here we have our story board and it's pretty blank.
所以这里我们拥有我们的 storyboard并且它是空白的
It looks blank there's this big blank square here.
它看起来是空的因为那里有很大一块空白的地方
This is our face view in here that I have selected.
在这里我选中的是我们的 face view
You can see the little resize handles are selected but
你可以看到小的调节手柄被选中了
I can't even really tell that's a face view.
但是我甚至不能告诉你那就是 face view
It's hard to tell where it is.
很难去描述出来他们在哪儿
It's just kinda hard to tell what's going on.
也很难描述出来他们将要到哪里去
And it's actually possible believe it or not to have your
然后它实际上可能相信它存在或者不存在
custom UI view subclasses draw in your story board.
去拥有你的自定义 UI view的 subclasses 在你的 storyboard里
Okay? So they can actually be
明白？所以他们实际上
live drawing in your storyboard.
已经在你的 stroyboard中被绘制了
And it's really incredibly easy to do.
而且它实际上这么做是令人难以置信的简单
I'm just gonna go back to my face view.
我准备返回我的 face view
Here it is.
它在这里
And right before the class here I'm gonna say
在这个类之前我准备探讨
at sign IBDesignable.
IBDesignable标记处的内容
And if I put at sign IBDesignable in there,
如果我在这里放置 IBDesignable标记
then when I go back to my storyboard,
然后当我返回我的 storyboard的时候
Xcode automatically notices that's an IB designable
Xcode 自动的识别那是一个 IB designable 类
class and it will draw it right here in the story board,
然后它会在 storyboard中的这里绘制它
so now I can see much more easily what's going on with my
所以现在我可以发现我的 faceview 会变得更加容易
face view, where it is here.
它是在这里
And if I change something in my face,
然后如果我在我的 face view中改变了什么的话
like let's go change that smile so it's not a frown.
类似于我们将笑脸换成不是皱眉的那个
Whoops where is that, it's right here, minus 0.5.
Whoops 哪里去了，它在这里，减掉0.5
Let's change that to plus 0.5.
让我们给它增加0.5
Then you'll notice that this file has changed and
然后一会发现这个文件被修改了
it will recompile it and redraw it.
随后它将会重新编译它并且重新绘制它
Okay so you're always seeing the latest version.
所以你可以始终看到最终的版本
Now another thing that would be really
现在这里还有另外一件事会很酷
cool here is just like if we have a button or a label.
就像如果我们拥有一个 button 或一个 label
When we bring up the attributes inspector here
当我们在这里设置属性窗口中的内容
we can edit attributes of a button or a label.
我们可以编辑 button或者 label的属性
Right? Like its alignment or its font.
明白？类似于它的对其方式或者字体
Well wouldn't it be cool if we could edit the attributes of
想象一下如果我们在这里可以编辑 face view的属性
this face view here as well?
会不会变得很酷
And we can do that too.
我们可以做到这一点
If we go back here to the face view here's some of
如果我们返回到face view的这里
the things that are setable about a face view.
这里是有一些地方是可以设置 face view的
The line width, the color, and the scale.
线宽，颜色，和比例
And you can make any of these things editable inside of your
并且你可以设置其中的任何一个属性在你的 storyboard中
storyboard by just putting in here i b inspectable.
通过仅仅是在这里放置 i b inspectable
But I'd be inspectable before them.
但我会在他们之前 放置inspectable
Then interface builder,
随后 interface builder，
which is the part of x code that is doing part of your
是Xcode的一部分会做 storyboard的部分工作
storyboard will create a new UI to make all those editable.
比如创建一个新的 UI使所有的这些可编辑
Here is our storyboard.
这里就是我们的 storyboard
Now if you look over here you can see face view.
现在如果你查看这里你可以看见 face view
It's added things to be able to set these.
它添加的东西才能够设置这些
I can set things like my line width.
我可设置很多比如我的线宽
Maybe I want thicker lines.
也许我想要加厚的线条
Maybe I want a different color.
也许我想要不同的颜色
So we can go to the color chooser here.
所以我们可以去颜色选择器
We could pick green color or orange or something like that.
我们可以选择绿色或者橙色或者类似的颜色
Tangerine.
橘黄色
It looks good.
看起来不错
And we can change the scale as well, too.
我们同样也可以改变比例
We can go down to 0.5, maybe we want to go 0.95, all right?
我们可以向下调整0.5，或者我们想要调整0.95，明白？
We can change that.
我们可以改变那个
Now, these are not only changing here in
现在，这些不仅仅是在你的storyboard中改变了
your storyboard, but they're actually setting the default
实际上他们在设置中参数也改变了
value so that when you run your application, so
这样当你运行你的应用的时候
let's go and run our application here.
现在让我们在这里运行我们的应用
It's going to use these values that are set in
它将会使用这些你在
the storyboard.
storyboard中设置的参数
Just like if those were buttons or labels and you had
就像如果这些是按钮或者文本然后
changed something about them in the inspector, it's going
你在inspector中改变了他们的一些参数
to change the way it works in your program as well.
它将会在你的程序中改变它的工作方式
Yes, questions.
有问题么？
>> So that overwrites what's in your code?
>> 所以在你的代码中重写了？
>> Yes, so the question is does that overwrite what's in
>> 好的，所以问题是在代码中
our code?
进行重写了？
So for example, back here.
举个例子，回到这里
We had equals three, we had equals blue color and
我们拥有相同的3个，我们有三个相同的蓝色
the answer is yes, it overrides it.
然后答案是是的，它重写了它
Basically, when interface loads it up it respects those.
从根本上来说，当 interface加载了它
It will use those but as soon as you start editing them,
它将会使用他们但是当你开始编辑他们的时候
then it's going to override them and
它将会 override他们并且
reset them to the editor value.
重置他们的值为编辑器的值
Any other questions about that?
还有其他关于这里的问题么？
Question?
还有问题么？
>> Yes, so the question is are there some,
>> 好的，所以问题是那里
there's got to be some got-yous, or something.
那里有一些你的或者一些东西
Why wouldn't it just be the ideal design be the default?
为什么不让它的默认值达到一个完美的设计
And, yes, there are some gotchas.
是的，那里有一些 gotchas
There's certain things that, really, it can't do.
还有某些事情，真的是，我做不了
It can't load your code up, you might have dependencies on
它不能加载你的代码，你也许有一些 dependencies在
other frameworks that it can't see, things like that.
其他的 frameworks上并且是看不到的，事情就像那样
So yeah, there are some gotchas,
所以，那里有一些 gotchas
I don't have time to go through them all but
我没有时间去把他们都经历一遍
I just wanted to show you that this is here for
但是我只是想要向你展示这里的东西
most straight forward sub class UI view,
大多数的是跟 UI view 类相关的
it works great without gotchas.
它在没有 gotchas的时候工作的很好
But yeah, there are obviously some times when it's not going
但是，在那里明显也有一些时候它不工作了
to work, because you could have a complicated view, so
以为你也许有一个复杂的视图
any other questions about it?
所以还有其他的问题么？
That's all there is to know about that.
这就是所有的关于这部分的内容
So let's go back to our model here, or
所以让我们回到我们的 model
to our controller, and I want to put the model in here for
或者我们的 controller，然后我想在这里放一个 model
the happiness view controller.
提供给 happiness view controller
So it's model, because this is demoed and
所以这里是 model，因为这是一个 demo
I want it all to be really quick and
并且我想要所以的变得很快
you can even follow along with me, some of you.
你甚至可以跟着我，你们中的一部分
This model's gonna be really simple.
这个 model 将会变得非常简单
I'm gonna have the model of and
我将要拥有 model
a model you know the model is right?
一个你知道的 model
Your calculator's model was a calculator brain so
你的计算器的 model 是一个计算器的大脑
it was a whole object that you created to be the model.
所以你建立的 model是一整个对象
Here I'm gonna have my model be the happiness and
在这里我准备使我的 model成为 happiness并且
it's going to be the very complicated data structure of
这将是一个非常复杂的数据结构
an int.
一个 int 型
Okay. So
好的，所以
we're gonna represent our happiness as an Int.
我们准备 represent我们的 happiness为一个 Int型
And I'm gonna start it out at 50.
所以我准备给它出来的值设定为50
And I'm gonna have my happiness mean 0 is very sad,
然后我准备设置我的 happiness为0的时候代表非常伤心
and 100 is ecstatic.
100的时候代表欣喜若狂
Okay?
明白？
So that's my model.
所以那是我的 model
Super duper simple model, and don't get this model confused
超级简单的一个 model，然后不要让这个 model感到困惑
with the smiliness in the face view,
在 face view中使用一个笑脸
that's a different thing, that's just the angle of
那是一件不同的事，这仅仅是
that arc in the face view, totally separate thing.
face view中 圆弧的角度，完全独立的东西
And you notice they're kind of on different scales anyways.
你注意到他们种在不同尺度上
This is 0 to 100,
这是 0到 100
the smiliness is minus 1 to positive 1, etc.
笑脸减1或者加1，等等
And that's okay because one of
那是没关系的因为
the things that controllers do, one of their jobs really,
事情中的一件事情由 controller做，他们中的任何一项工作
is to interpret the model for the view.
是由 model interpret给 view 的
Okay, or vice versa in what happens in the view.
好的，反之在该视图会发生什么
And they have to figure out what to
他们必须弄清楚
communicate to the model.
去用什么和 model沟通
That's a lot of what a controller does.
controller做的是一件很大的工作
And so, we're going to have some coding here,
所以，我们准备在这里添加一些代码
that does exactly that.
这正是这么做的
Interprets our 0 to 100 happiness into a smile or not.
Interprets 我们的 0 到 100 进入一个笑脸或者不进入
Now there's other things that
现在有其他的事情
represent happiness besides smiling.
represent happiness 除了 smiling
You know, little crinkly eyes.
你知道的，有点弯曲的眼睛
And other things that make you appear that you're happy.
和其他的东西，让你看来是快乐的
But we're just gonna use our face view which only knows how
但我们只是要去使用我们的 face view 它只知道怎样
to smile or not.
去微笑或者不微笑
Now one thing that we can do inside this model.
现在在这个 model中有一件事我们可以做
I put the curly braces here and
我在这里添加一个大括号然后
you might say why did I put that there?
你可能会问我为什么我把它放在这里？
That is because I want to use the property observer for
那是因为我想要对我的 model使用属性观察器
my model to, essentially, validate my model.
实质上，验证我的 model
So you can use property observers to do evaluation,
所以你可以使用属性观察期去进行评估
really, of any property that you want.
任何你想查看的属性
So my happiness can only be 0 to a 100.
所以我的 happiness 只能在 0 到 100内
If someone passes me happiness minus 1 or
如果一个人传给我的 happiness 负1或者
5,000 I need to kind of keep it in range to 0 to 100.
5000 我需要将它保持在 0到100的范围内
So I'm just going to say, in my setter here,
所以，我只是想说，在我的 setter中
my property observer here,
我的属性观察期中
I'm going to say min max of my happiness to 0 or 100,
我想说在我的 happiness中最小和最大的值是 0和100
so I'm just keeping it between zero and a hundred, right?
因此我将把它保持在0到100之间, 对么?
So no matter what someone passes me -1 or 5000,
无论输入了-1还是5000.
my happiness won't ever be outside of that.
我的"开心指数" 永远不会超出范围.
Again, this is kind of a trivial example.
再说一遍, 这是一个很简易的例子.
You might have a much powerful model that
你可以有个更强大的Model.
needs much more powerful validation than this,
需要比这更严谨的评估.
but you can see this as a place to put it.
但是你能把它(这个Model)看做一个可行的方案.
Another thing you might want to have here is if someone
你可能想做的另一件事情是
updates your model, you might want to update your UI.
如果有人改变了你的Model, 你可能想要更新你的UI.
Okay, so I'm going to have update UI,
好的, 因此我将升级UI.
and I'm just going to have a function down here, update UI,
我将在下面这里加一个函数(Function), 叫updateUI.
and it's going to do something to update the user interface,
它将会负责更新用户界面.
and that's a common thing.
更新UI是一件很寻常的事情.
When your model changes,
当你的Model改变时,
you want your controller to cause the UI to be updated.
你想让你的Controller将UI更新.
I think I'm going to put in here also is a little println
我还会在这里加个println() 命令,
happiness equals back slash happiness.
Happiness =\  happiness.
Just so we can see our happiness changing in our
这样我们总是能在接下来的演示中,
console all the time as we work the rest of the demos.
在console(控制台)中看到happiness的变化.
So we'll work on this update UI piece when we
好的,在我们回到demo之前,
get back to the demos.
解决更新UI这部分.
I just wanted to show you the model of happiness.
我就是想向你们展示Happiness的Model.
Right now it's not hooked up to a it's UI.
现在, Model 并没有和UI关联.
So if I run my application,
因此, 如果我现在运行应用
you'll see that this is not happiness of 50.
你们将会看到(结果)并不是50.
This is not even looking at the happiness.
甚至看上去不像是笑脸.
I could change this to anything that I want and
我可以把这个变成任何我想要的值
it's not going to change this.
但是这并不会改变运行结果.
And so later we'll show you how we hook up our UI
所以, 稍后我会向你们展示如何通过Controller连接UI.
to our model through our controller,
与Model关联.
that's one of the main things a controller does.
这个是Controller的主要功能之一.
Okay, so let's go back to our slides though.
好的, 现在我们回到幻灯片.
All right here, I'm going to start with this miscellaneous
好的, 我将以这个混杂的
topic here, kind of a bonus topic, which is extensions.
主题开始, 类似于额外的主题, 它就是extensions(扩展).
You read about in your reading assignments, so
你已经在阅读作业里读到过了.
you know what this is,
你知道它是什么.
hopefully you've been reading those reading assignments.
希望你们一直以来都完成了阅读作业.
But I'm discovering here in class,
但是我在课中发现,
not as much because it's an important feature per se but
并不与它本身本身的重要性相称
it can be a little bit of a dangerous feature so
它(extensions)有时会变得有点危险,
I wanted to cover it a little bit.
因此我想讲一点这个.
So an extension is really simple.
extensions 真得很简单.
It's just a little syntax, to add methods and properties to
它就是一个给一个现存类(class), 结构(structure)
existing classes, structures, and enums.
和枚举(enums) 添加新方法或属性的小语法.
Okay? You do not have to
好么? 你不是必须要
have the source code to those things you're adding it to.
有目标的源代码.
You could just add these methods and
你可以就把这些方法和属性
properties pretty much at will.
凭想法加入.
There are some restrictions, one is that you can't add via
这里有些限制, 其中之一是
an extension a method or property that already exists.
你不能通过一个已存在的方法或特性添加extensions.
So it's not a way to replace it, this is not sub classing,
因此这不是一个替换的手段, 这也不是创建子类,
you're not replacing or overwriting methods, so
你不能替换或者覆盖一个方法, 因此
this has to be something where the property or
这些你想添加进类的的
method you wanna add to a class.
属性或方法
Does not exist.
必须是之前不存在的.
The second thing is that any
第二个是
properties you add cannot have any storage.
你添加的属性不能有存储.
Okay so they can only be computed properties,
好么? 因此这些属性只能是运算属性.
right the get, set, kind.
set 和 get 方法这类的.
That's the only kind of property you can have.
那是你唯一能添加的一种属性.
Okay, but inside an extension otherwise it kind of
好的, 但是在一个extension中, 相反, 它
looks like you're in the definition of class.
看起来有点像你在定义类.
You can refer to self if you want and
你可以把它指向self,如果你想,
that will be the thing that you are extending.
这样它就是你扩展的对象.
It's a pretty powerful feature actually.
这实际上是一个很强大的特性.
This feature is easily abused however people putting all
但是这个特性容易被误用, 人们把
kinds of adding methods to classes making it so it's
一些方法加进类里把它变得
completely not understandable of what that does anymore.
完全不能理解它是做什么的.
It's also whoever designed the class thinks a lot about it,it's
另外, 设计这个类的人考虑了很多关于
API and what should be in it and what shouldn't and
它的API 和它应包含的和不包含的内容
now all of the sudden things are being added.
但是现在突然加了这么多东西.
That's kind of weird.
这有些奇怪.
This is really best used for beginners like you
它对你们这些初学Swift的人
who are just starting with SWIFT to add little
最有用的地方是加入一些
helper functions to enhance the readability of your code.
小的help function(帮助函数)以增强代码的可读性.
Okay, so if there's something that it would be
好的, 如果cgrect能做这件事
really great if a cgrect could do this little thing, you
那么真的会很棒.
could add a little extension to a cgrect to do that.
你可以给cgrect加个extension来做到这点.
Or maybe a UI view controller just once.
或者给UI view controller 加一次.
This extra little property that it can calculate about itself.
这个额外的属性能计算它本身的.
That's the kind of thing that you could use it for.
这些是你能用extensions做到的事情.
Now extensions actually can be used by advanced Swift users
现在extensions实际上能被进阶Swift用户
to architects or, for architects, to really organize all your code.
用来整理或设计全部代码.
Because you can
因为你可以
put almost everything into extensions, and
把几乎所有的东西放在extensions中
use extensions as basically groupings of functionality.
并且把extensions基本等同于给功能分组来用.
And so, it's really a powerful feature and
因此它真的是非常强大的特性.
I don't want to make it sound like it's only for
我不想让它听起来好像
little kinda dribes and drabs add tiny little helper things.
它只能零碎地加些帮助注释.
It can actually be used as a core foundation of how you
它能被当做核心基础使用,
architect.
来帮助你规划.
But that does require some one to sit down and
但是完成它需要某人坐下来
have an architectural plan to do that and
并且有一个设计计划.
you obviously a little early in the game to be doing that.
现在你们这样做很显然有点早了.
So I would say, when in doubt, if you're not sure whether or
因此, 我会说, 如果你有点迷惘,
not you should make something an extension,
不知道这里是否要加extensions,
don't do it for now.
现在这个阶段就不用加了.
And over time, you'll get more comfortable with it,
随着时间, 你会越来越适应是用它,
you'll understand what to do.
你会明白怎么做.
And again, the syntax for
再说一遍, 它的语法
it is all explained in the documentation.
全部在文件里写得清清楚楚.
Maybe in the demo here, I'll try and throw one in, so
可能在今天的演示里, 我会加一个.
you can see what it looks like.
这样的话你们会明白它到是什么样的.
That was just an aside,
这些只是顺带提一提,
now let's get back to the main guts, okay?
现在我们回到真正的干货, 好么?
This very important feature called delegation,
有个非常重要的特性叫做委托(delegation)
I have to teach you about protocols first,
我先要教你们协议(protocols),
again you probably read about this in reading assignments,
你们应该已经在阅读作业里读到过这些了,
but I want to go over it anyway.
无论怎样我重头说一遍,
A protocol is basically a way to express your
一个协议基本上是
API a little more minimally.
一种相对简便的表示API的方法.
Not to drag in so much API by, for example,
不是通过添加比如
having an argument to a function be a class where now
传递一个代表类的参数给函数,
you're passing an entire class into that function,
你把整个类传递给了那个函数.
who knows what that function might do with that class.
谁知道那个函数会让那个类做什么.
It could access the entire non private API of that thing.
函数很能会访问类的所有的非私有API.
So really, the function just wants to use the one method of
所以, 说真的, 这个函数只是想用类中
a class.
的一个方法而已.
Protocols are a way for
协议是函数的一种表达方式,
the function to express or really, I just want you to
或者, 我只是想让你给我
pass me something that can do this one function.
一些能让这个函数运作的东西.
Because that's what I'm going to call in here.
因为我要再这里调用这些东西.
So, it's a way to kind of minimize your API.
所以, 这是一个简化API的方法.
A protocol is a type.
一个协议是一个数据类型.
Okay, it's just like a class, or an enum, or a struct.
就像一个class, 或者enums, 或者struct.
Okay. It's a type.
好么, 它是一个数据类型.
It can be used everywhere a type is.
它可以被用在任何数据类型能用的地方.
A type of an argument to a function.
一个函数的参数,
A var or a let can be a protocol.
一个变量或者一个let 也能是一个协议.
Type. So it is absolutely a type.
类型, 因此它绝对是一个数据类型.
The only thing that is interesting about it is it
唯一一个有趣的地方是,
has no implementation.
协议本身是没有实现的.
Okay?
好么?
In fact, it's kind of the definition of a protocol,
事实上, 这类似于协议的定义.
it's a type with no implementation.
这是一个没有实现的数据类型.
It only has declaration.
它只有声明
Use a protocol to declare various properties and
用协议来声明很多变量
methods but it has no implementation.
和方法, 但是没有相应的实现.
The implementation is provided by other objects that conform
"实现"是由其它遵从协议的对象
to the protocol.
提供的.
Okay, and there might be
好的, 可能会有成百个
hundreds of objects that will conform to a certain protocol.
遵从某同一个协议的对象,
Okay?
好么?
But the protocol when you use it looks just like a type,
但是, 协议在使用的时候看起来就是个数据类型.
exactly like a type as you're gonna see here.
你们将会看到, 跟数据类型一模一样.
Now there's three aspects to a protocol, to using one.
这有三个使用协议的条件.
One is the declaration of the protocol.
一个是协议的声明.
This looks a lot like declaring your class or
这看起来很像声明你的class,
an enum or struct.
或者enums或者struct.
It's just that there is no implementations for
它仅仅是没有任何属性或方法
any of the properties or methods.
的实现.
Then there's the declaration part where a class or
接着, 声明的部分会出现,
a struct or an enum says, I will implement this protocol.如果一个class, struct 或者enum说我会实现这个协议.
So it declares that it will conform to, or implement,
因此它声明它会遵从或者实现
this protocol.
这个协议.
And then there's the part where that class, struct or
接着, 在class, struct 或者enum
enum actually implements the protocol.
会有负责实现协议的部分.
So, it implements that, all the properties and
所以, 它会实现, 所有在协议中需要的
methods in the protocol that's required, all of them.
属性和方法, 所有的.
Okay?
好么?
So we'll see what that looks like in some code.
我们会在几行代码里看到(协议)到底是怎样.
So here's a declaration of a protocol itself, okay?
这里是协议自身的声明, 好么?
The protocol's called some protocol, all right?
这个协议叫做"某个协议"(Some protocol), 好么?
This protocol has really what some might call
这个协议有些叫做
inherited protocols, or a protocol that inherits.
继承协议,或者, 一个协议它能够继承.
Which are other protocols that if you want to implement some
如果你想要实现某些协议,
protocol you have to implement those too.
你必须也将这些继承协议实现.
Okay that's what this colon thing, so
这就是代码里冒号所代表的.
it kind of looks like this super class kind of thing but
这感觉上有点像父类,
there can be multiple of them, but it's not really
但是能够有很多不同的继承协议.
inherent in this, per se, like you think of in classes, it's
继承协议并不是跟你想象中的类那样
more just saying if you want to implement some protocol you
我想说的是, 如果你想要实现协议,
also have to implement inherited protocol one and
你必须还要实现继承协议1
inherited protocol two.
以及继承协议2.
If you don't implement those then you
如果你没有实现这些, 也就是
haven't implemented all of some protocol.
没有实现所有的协议.
Okay?好么?
Now you have to specify, when you do a property,
现在你必须明确, 当你设计一个属性,
you don't put the implementation there but
你并不加入实现部分
you have to classify whether this is a get only property or
但是你必须区分这是一个只有get的属性
it's a get and set, okay?
还是既有get也有set.
The system needs to know whether it's
系统需要知道它是否是一个set方法
a set because structs and enums are value types and
因为structs和enums都是数据类型并且
it needs to know when it's being mutated so
它需要知道什么时候被改变
it can copy them and etcetera, okay?这样的话它才能复制和其他之类的, 好么?
Any functions that are expected to mutate also need
任何可能会被更改的函数还需要
to be noted with this mutating keyword, okay?
用这个mutating关键字标注
You probably read that in the description,
你可能在描述文件里读到了.
you know that structs and enums,
你知道structs和enums,
insert value types, the system needs to know when a function
插入值类型, 系统需要知道函数
is actually changing them, so they can copy it on demand.
具体什么时候会改变它们, 这样它们能根据需求复制.
It is possible to limit your protocol to only work
限制你的协议只能和类一起
with classes.
工作是可行的
You put the word class right after that colon.
你把class这个词放在那个冒号后面,
So SomeProtocol colon class means this protocol can
这样"SomeProtocol: class" 意味着
only be implemented by a class.
它只能被类实现.
It cannot be implemented by a struct or an enum.
它不能被一个struct或者enum实现.
Okay? Then you wouldn't need
好么? 这样你不需要
any mutatings because a class,
任何 mutatings，因为这是一个类
since it's a reference passed by reference all the time,
这是个引用，并且一直以引用被传递
you can obviously mutate with any method or property.
因此你可以通过任何方法或者属性进行 mutate
Okay, you can even specify that
你甚至可以设计
a protocol requires the class or
一个协议，要求类或
structure enum to implement a certain initializer.
结构枚举去实现特定的初始化函数
Okay, that way you
通过这种方式，你知道你可以创建
know that you can create one of these things.
这些东西中的一个
All right. So, that's kinda cool too.
这非常酷
All right, so that's how you declare a protocol.
这就是你要怎样声明一个协议
See? It's pretty straightforward.
看到了吗？非常直观
No implementations in here, right?
这里没有 implementations
All right, so now let's talk about the part of it where it
现在我们来讲这部分
says I'm an implementor.
称作 implementor
I want to implement this protocol.
我想实现这个协议
How do I tell the world I'm going to implement this?
我怎么告诉这个世界我要实现它？
You do that by putting at
要实现它，你要将它放在
the end of the declaration of the thing, so here's class,
声明的末尾。这是个类
SomeClass then it inherits from SuperclassOfSomeClass.
SomeClass 继承自 SuperclassOfSomeClass
You just put a comma and all the protocols that
你可以放个逗号，还有这个类将要实现的
this class is claiming to implement, okay?
所有协议
Now, obviously if this was a struct or
显然，这是个结构或者枚举
enum it wouldn't have that superclass name.
它没有父类
So it would just be colon and then the list of
因此，它就只有一个冒号
all the protocols that it is claiming to implement.
还有它将实现的所有协议
So this enum says it's going to implement some protocol,
这个枚举将实现一些协议
and it's also going to implement another protocol.
同时它也将实现另一些协议
And once it says that, it has to do it or
一旦它声明了，它就必须实现（协议）
the compiler will not allow you to compile, okay?
否则编译器不让你通过编译
Same thing with the struct, all right?
结构也是一样的
So pretty straightforward syntax there.
这是非常直观的语法
The number of protocols is unlimited,
协议的数量是无限的
you can just keep putting more and
你可以保留你将实现的日益增多的
more protocols that you say you'll implement.
协议
In a class, if you implement an init in a class,
在一个类中，如果你实现了一个类的初始化函数
you have to say it's required.
你必须使用 required（关键字）
Okay?
So that's because you wouldn't want a subclasser
这是因为你不想一个子类使用
using the rules of inheritance of initializers which we
初始化函数的继承规则，这个我们
talked about in depth last lecture or the one before.
在上次课或上上次课有深入讲解过
It can get to a situation where that init is
这有可能导致这样一种情况：子类
not even implemented, okay, in sub class.
没有实现初始化函数
And that would be no good because you're saying
这样不好，因为你遵循了
you conform to this protocol and then that init is part of
这个协议，那初始化函数就是协议的一部分
this protocol so you have to make them required.
所以你必须将它们标为 required
Okay?
You are allowed to add protocol compliance or
你可以使用 extension 来添加
conformance with an extension.
协议的一致性
And this is very common to do,
这很常用
again, in a bigger architected system, is you will implement
在一个大一点的架构系统中，你在类或结构枚举上
the entire implementation of a protocol on some class or
实现整个协议的内容是
structure enum by implementing it as an extension.
通过 extension 来实现的
Now the only thing about that implementation is,
现在关于 implementation 的唯一事情是
of course, no stored properties in there.
当然，这里没有存储属性
Only computer properties.
只有计算性的属性
So you would have to be able to
所以你不需要任何存储就能够实现
implement that entire protocol without any storage.
整个协议
But a lot of protocols can be implemented without storage.
但很多协议可以不需要任何存储就实现了
Cuz they're fairly simple protocols, okay.
它们是些相当简单的协议
Here's what it looks like to use a protocol as a type.
这里，看起来像是将协议当作一个类型来用
So I've created a protocol called Moveable.
我已创建了一个协议，叫做 Moveable
It has one function in it,
它有一个函数
move to, which presumably moves the thing.
moveTo，这个函数大概是移动这个东西的
I've created two things,
我创建了两个东西
a class called car which is a moveable.
一个叫做 car 的类，这是一个 Moveable
So the car can be moved, and a class called,
因此这个 car 可以被移动，还有一个类
or struct rather called shape which can be moveable, so this
更确切的说是结构，叫做 shape，这个可以被移动
might be a graphical shape that can be moved on screen.
这可能是一个可以在屏幕上被移动的图形形状
Now you see that car and
现在你看到 car 和
shape are completely different kinds of things, but
shape 是两个完全不同的东西
they both could be moved, so they both could be movables.
但它们都能被移动，所以它们都是可以移动的
And you can see that they both properly implement the movable
你们看，它们都正确地实现了 movable 协议
protocol and they both claimed implement movable.
它们都声明实现了 movable
Then I've created a couple of little variables here prius
然后我创建了几个变量，prius 和
and square which are just instances of car and shape.
square，是 car 和 shape 的实例
Okay, so now let's look at some code.
现在我们看一些代码
I can create a variable called thing to move.
我可以创建一个变量，叫做 thingToMove
It is of type moveable.
这是 moveable 类型
That's protocol, but protocols are types.
那是协议，但协议都是类型
And I can set it equal to prius.
我可以让它等于 prius
This is completely legal because a prius
这是完全合法的，因为一个 prius
is a moveable, right?
就是一个 moveable
It implements the moveable protocol.
它实现了 moveable 协议
So I can set a variable that is moveable to a prius,
因此我可以讲一个 moveable 的变量赋值 prius
works great.
非常棒
I can then say thing to move, move to.
然后我可以使用 thingToMove.moveTo()
Because thing to move is anything that implements
因为 thingToMove 是一个实现了 moveable
the moveable protocol.
协议的任何东西
However, I cannot say thing to move dot change oil, okay?
然而，我不能使用 thingMoveTo.changeOil()
Change oil is a car thing,
changOil 是 car 的方法
it's not a moveable thing, okay?
不是 moveable 的方法
So I can't send it to a moveable.
所以我不能在 moveable 中调用它
Even though, yes,
尽管如此
that thing to move happens to currently contain a car
这个 thingToMove 恰好包含了一个 car
it's still a compiler won't even let you put this in.
编译器不会让你这样使用
It'll complain.
它会报错
It'll say, thing to move is a moveable.
它会说，thingToMove 是一个 moveable
Moveables don't understand change oil.
Moveable 不懂 changeOil
You understand?
明白了吗？
I could then say thingToMove equal square.
我可以让 thingToMove ＝ square
That's perfectly legal as well cuz a square is a Moveable.
这是相当合法的，因为 square 是一个 Moveable
It implements that protocol so it can do it as well.
它实现了这个协议，所以这也是可以的
More interestingly I could let thingsToMove be an array of
更有趣的是，我可以让 thingsToMove 为 [Moveable]
Moveable, and I could set it equal to an array that
让它等于包含 prius 和 square 的
has a prius anda square in it.
一个数组
So it's got a car and a shape, a class and a struct,
所以它有一个 car 和 shape，一个类和一个结构
all in this array and it's perfectly legal because
都在这个数组中，这是合法的
they're both moveable so I can create an array of them
因为它们都是 moveable，因此我可以创建关于它们的数组
because moveable is a protocol It's just like a type.
moveable是一个协议，如同一种类型
It is a type.
它就是一种类型
Okay, make sense?
有道理吧？
Why I can do that?
为什么我能这样做？
All right I can also have a function like slide,
我也可以有一个函数 slide
let's say that slide something along the ground or
就是在地上或其他地方滑动某物
something, and you can take an argument which is unmovable.
你可以使用不是 moveable 的参数
And then inside of it I can say move to and
然后在函数里面，我可以使用 moveTo
that works fine, and I say slide prius,
这能正常工作，我可以使用 slide(prius)
slide square, all works fine because.
slide(square)，都能正常工作
They're all moveable.
它们都是 moveable
It's actually possible to declare an argument like slip
世界上，声明一个 slipAndSlide 是可以的
and slide, that implements two, that takes an argument
这个实现了两个，带一个参数，这个参数
that has to implement two separate protocols.
必须实现两个不同的协议
Moveable, but also something called slippery, let's say,
Moveable，还有 Slippery，Slippery这个
which I haven't defined.
我还没定义
Okay, so
this little thing where you say protocol angle bracket and
这个东西，你使用 protocol <，然后很多你想
then as many protocols as you want closed angle bracket,
实现的协议，最后以 > 结束
that says this argument to this function has to implement
这表明这个参数必须实现
both of those protocols.
这些协议中的两个
Or all of those protocols.
或者所有这些协议
And then if I tried to say slip and
如果我试图使用 slipAndSlide(prius)
slide Prius, not even compile.
是不能通过编译的
Because while Prius is a moveable,
因为 prius 是一个 moveable
it's not as slippery.
不是 slippery
And so it can't do that.
所以不能这么做
Can't be passed through that argument, okay?
不能传递这个参数
Everyone cool with protocols?
每个人都理解协议了吗？
Any question about that before I
在我开始讲解使用协议的代理（delegation）前，还有人
start talking about delegation which uses protocols?
有问题吗？
Okay. So
delegation is a very important use of protocols.
代理是协议的一个非常重要用途
Delegation, if you remember back to our MVC talk right at
代理，如果你记得我们这节课刚开始讲的 MVC
the beginning of the quarter, we had this big graph.
我们有这个大图表
And one of the things we showed was how views need to
我们讲的其中一点是，views 如何和它们的
be able to talk back to their controller, okay?
controller 通讯
But views are generic.
但 views 是普通的
So, they can't know anything about the class or
它们不知道使用它们的
the controller that's using them.
类或者 controller
They're generic building blocks.
它们是普通的积木
Okay? So how do they talk back?
它们是怎么通讯的？
Well, it turns out they talk back using protocols, okay,
实际上它们使用协议进行通信
and this is called delegation.
这个叫做代理
Okay?
So, let's talk a little bit about how that works,
让我们讲讲这是如何工作的
how it plays out to do delegation.
代理是怎么玩的
First, you're gonna create the delegate protocol.
首先，你要创建一个代理协议
So, the delegate protocol is just gonna be protocol,
这个代理协议是一个协议
something with a bunch of methods and
包含了许多方法，也
perhaps even properties.
可能包含属性。
And it's going to describe what the view is looking for
它描述了这个 view 要别人帮
someone else to do for it.
它做的事情
Okay?
It's gonna describe the responsibilities the view is
它描述了 view 要代理给其他人的
going to delegate to someone else.
职责
Okay? So if this is a scroll view,
这是一个 scroll view
something the protocol might be, should scroll to point.
这个协议可能是，应该滚动到一个点
The view wants to know should I scroll to this point?
这个 view 想知道我是否要滚动到这个点？
The user's trying to scroll to this point.
用户试图滚动到这个点
Should I do it?
我应该处理这个吗？
And the view doesn't know because it
view 并不知道，因为它不拥护
doesn't own its own data.
自己的数据
It doesn't really even know what it's scrolling on.
它甚至不知道它在什么东西上滚动
It needs to ask someone else.
它需要询问别人
So it's going to create this protocol.
所以它要创建这个协议
Any time it either needs to notify someone else to
任何时候，它需要告知别人正在发生的有趣的
something interesting that is happening or
事情，或者它
ask someone else for permission to do something or
向他人请求权限去做一些事情或
to try to get its data, which is a common thing.
获取自己的数据，这是非常常见的
It wants its data that it's trying to draw but
它需要它尝试绘图的数据，但
it can't own its own data.
它没有自己的数据
Remember views can't own their data,
记住 views 不能有自己的数据
the data is owned by the controller.
数据是被 controller 拥有的
Really, it's probably in the model, but
实际上，数据可能在 model 中
the controller is responsible for dishing the data out.
但 controller 负责取出数据
So at first you're gonna create that protocol.
因此首先你要创建协议
Then you're gonna create a property in your view,
然后你要在 view 中创建一个属性
okay, called delegate or sometimes it's called data
称作代理或者有时叫做数据源
source if it's delegating the data.
如果它代理数据的话
And the type of that property is
然后这个属性的类型是这个
this delegation protocol that you're gonna create.
你将创建的代理协议
Protocols are just types so
协议就是类型，就是属性将被
that's what the property type is gonna be.
声明的类型
Okay, then it's gonna use that property to go do all
然后它将使用这个属性去处理
the delegation.
所有的代理
It's going to send a message to
它将发送一个消息给代理属性
the delegate property saying, should I scroll to this point,
我是否要滚动到这个点
it's going to send a message to this delegate property.
它将发送一条消息给代理属性
Maybe it will be called data source in this case, but
这个例子中它大概叫做 dataSource，但
it's saying hey, where's my data?
它询问，我的数据在哪里？
Give me more of my data.
给我更多我的数据
Okay? That's what it's going to
明白了吗？这就是它将要
send and it's going to send it to this object right here,
发送的消息，而且，它将会把这个消息发送给这里的对象
this delegate property.
也就是这个 delegate 属性
And this delegate property, all it is is a protocol.
然后，这个 delegate 属性，完全就是一种协议
So all that, anybody who implements that
所以，只要是任何遵循这个协议的对象
protocol can be set as the value for that.
都可以对这个属性设值
Delegate.
All right then the controller is going to come along and
好的，接下来的是控制器
it's going to first say that it implements that protocol.
控制器首先会说，它自身实现了这个协议
Okay, so it's a class thing, it's going to say, yeah,
由于它是一个类，那么它会说
I implement this view this delegate protocol.
我实现了这个视图的代理协议的方法
Then the controller is going to
接着，控制器将
set it's self as the delegate.
会将它自身作为代理对象
So it's going to set that delegate property inside
它会设置这个视图的代理属性为其自身
the view to itself, which is fine because it just said it
这里没有任何问题，因为刚刚说了，它
implements that protocol, so that's good.
声明自己已经实现了这个协议所需的方法
Then, of course,
接下来，当然
the controllers going to have to implement the protocol, and
这个控制器将填充这些方法，这些协议方法的具体实现细节
implement all the methods and properties required by
并不一定要实现协议规定的所有方法，但是
the protocol so that it conforms to that protocol.
一定需要实现这个协议必需（required）的方法
Otherwise compiler is going to complain.
否则编译器会报错
And you're good to go.
这就可以了
Now the view is hooked up to the controller, okay?
现在，这个视图已经和控制器建立关系了，明白了吗？
But the view still knows nothing about the controller.
但是视图仍旧不知道控制器是什么东西
It doesn't know what class it is.
不知道控制器的类是什么
It doesn't know what its purpose in life is.
不知道控制器的目的是什么
It knows nothing.
什么都不知道
All it knows is it implements the methods in its protocol,
唯一知道的是，这个控制器实现了视图中的协议必需的方法
in the views protocol.
That's all it knows and that's all it needs to know.
这就是所有它想知道的，和它应该知道的
Okay? So that keeps
明白了吗？
the view completely generic and allows the controller to
这种模式，就让这个视图完全变得通用起来，同时也让控制器
have complete control of this generic minion in its view.
对这个视图有完全的控制
Remember the view is the controller's minions,
还记得吗？形象地说，视图就是控制器的傀儡
it's how it's communicating with the user.
这就是它如何跟用户打交道的
So that's how we do it.
以上就是我们如何做的
So let's take a look at a demo of doing that in happiness.
让我们看看在 Happiness 这个 Demo 中如何做这些操作
We're going to have
首先，我们需要
the face view delegate getting its data.
创建一个用于 faceView 来获取其数据的代理对象
Its data is basically its smiliness,
这个数据基本上就是它的笑容程度
how much smileyness is going on.
笑得多灿烂的程度
It's going to get that from the delegate.
这就是 faceView 想从这个代理对象中获取的
And, of course, the happiness view controller is going to
当然，happiness view controller 将会是
be the delegate it gets it from.
成为它的代理，提供数据
>> Okay.
好的
Well, let's now use delegation to hook up our
让我们来使用代理模式来连接
face view to our happiness view controller.
我们的 faceView 和我们的 happiness view controller
And we're gonna do that by
我们将会
starting here in the face view.
从 faceView 开始
We're gonna go through the same steps we
根据我们刚才说的流程
just talked about in the slides to do delegation.
来创建代理的关系
So remember the first step is that we need a protocol,
还记得第一个方法吗？首先我们需要一个协议
some particular way that the face view is going to talk to
一些具体的方式，让我们的 faceView 与
whoever's going to provide its data, and
任何一个可以提供数据的对象进行沟通
the face view's data is really it's smiliness.
这里的数据就是笑容的灿烂度
So the face view has this data.
现在 faceView 已经有这个数据了
Now this is a very, very simple data.
这个非常简单的常量
Probably in real life if this weren't,
或许在实际中这个并不是一个简单的常量
you know a demo where I'm trying to show you delegation,
但是，这里毕竟只是一个演示代理模式的 Demo
you would probably just set this, you
你可以就简单设置成一个常量
can't own it's own data, it's such a simple piece of data.
你不能拥有这个数据，它非常简单
But we're going to use delegation to
但我们将会使用代理来
get this piece of data here.
获得这里的数据
Rather than have it be set right here.
而不是直接在这里设值
All right, so
好的
we need some sort of protocol that gets this smiliness from
所以， 我们需要一些协议，来从某些对象中获取我的笑容程度
someone and, so we're gonna type in here protocol and
这里我们输入 protocol
I'm gonna call this protocol.
这里我打算叫这个协议为
That I'm developing my face view data source protocol.
因为这里我正在做的是我的 faceView 的数据来源协议，所以叫 FaceViewDataSource
And sometimes we call these delegation protocols delegate.
通常我们将代理类型的协议后缀名起为 Delegate
Like face view delegate.
类似于 FaceViewDelegate
But when the only purpose of the protocol is to
但这里这个协议唯一的作用就是
get the data that the view is going to draw.
获得这个视图用来绘制的一些数据
Because the view can't own its own data,
因为这个视图不能拥有这个数据
then we often will call the protocol datasource.
通常这种情况，我们称这种协议为 DataSource
So this just needs to have whatever functions and
所以。这里需要的就是
properties are required to get this used data.
用来获取数据的一些必需的函数和属性
Well such a simple view that it
这里，这么一个简单的视图
just needs something to get the smile in some function so
只需要一个用来获取笑容灿烂度的函数
I'm going to say smiliness for face view.
这里我输入 smilinessForFaceView
I have an argument here which is the sender.
这里有一个参数，也就是 sender
Face view.
FaceView
And this is gonna be myself.
这里会是这个控制器自身
So when I ask somebody else to provide my data by
当我要求其他的对象来提供我的数据的时候
sending them this message.
我发送这个消息
I'm gonna pass myself, this face view,
我将传入 self，这个FaceView
along as an argument.
作为其参数
And you'll see all throughout iOS when they have
你在 iOS 开发中会看到
a delegate or a data source.
当某个对象拥有一个 Delegate 或者 DataSouce 的时候
They are always going to pass themselves along.
他们都会传入他们自身
If you are trying to provide the smiliness for
如果你尝试给这个 FaceView 提供笑容的灿烂度的时候
this FaceView, you have a point or two to FaceView.
你将这个参数指向 FaceView
You know, which FaceView is asking you that, and
你知道的，这个 FaceView 要求你这个
maybe if you need to ask the FaceView some other
当然也许你也可以要求 FaceView 其他的问题
questions to answer this, you can do that.
来回答这个，当然你可以这么做
Now, this smiliness what is it going to return?
现在，这个 smiliness 方法，它会返回什么呢？
Now I'm going to have it return a double,
我想让它返回一个 Double
which is going to be that smiliness,
也就是笑容的灿烂度
remember that smiliness goes from a plus 1 down to minus 1,
还记得笑容的灿烂度从-1到+1吗？
plus 1 that's very smiley and
+1代表很开心
minus 1 that's very frowny and so we made that double.
-1代表很不开心，我们设置它为 Double
I'm also going to make this double be an optional.
同时，我将设置它为一个可选的 Double
And that's because if the data source, if I ask it for
那是因为，它作为一个 DataSource，如果我问
the smiliness, and for
它要灿烂度的时候
some reason it can't provide that smiliness, then I'm gonna
因为某些的原因，它无法提供相应的值
allow them to return nill, and just have no smile or
那么我允许它们返回 nil，也就是说
no frown, just flatlined mouth there.
既不是开心也不是不开心，一条线的嘴巴
Now we only by the way pass one argument here.
这里我们只传入了一个参数
But we could definitely, if we were asking our data source,
但是我们完全可以，如果我们在请求我们的 DataSource 的时候
we could have some more arguments in here.
可以使用多个参数
And so that's perfectly reasonable.
而且这么做也是完全合理的
You can have as many arguments as you
你为了从 DataSource 中获取这个笑容的灿烂度，需要多少个
need to get this smiliness out of the data source.
参数都可以
Okay, so that's step one, we have this data source here.
好的，这就是步骤一，我们这里已经有了 DataSource
Step two is we need to have a public var in our face view,
第二步是，我们需要在我们的 FaceView 中有一个公开的变量
which I'm going to call dataSource, and
这里我将称之为 dataSource
it's going to be of type FaceViewDataSource.
它的类型是 FaceViewDataSource
Okay?
明白了吗？
I'm going to make that an optional as well.
同样我这里会把它的类型变成可选的
So you can see here that I'm using FaceViewDataSource,
这里你可以看到，我将 FaceViewDataSource
which is this protocol, just as a type.
这个协议，作为一个类型
And what this means is,
这代表的是
somebody who wants to provide my data,
某个对象想要提供给我数据
who wants to be my dataSource,
也就是想成为我的 dataSource
all they need to do is set themselves as this variable.
那么，它们仅仅是需要将它们自身设置为这个变量的值
And then I'm going to talk to them through this variable to
接着，我可以通过这个变量来向它们发送消息
call this function on them.
来调用它们的某些函数
Okay?
明白了吗？
Now, why did I make this an optional here?
为什么这里我让它变成一个可选类型呢？
Because it's possible that
因为有可能
I can just live without a data source.
我们的 FaceView 并没有一个 dataSource
I will just always have a flat line, a flat mouth.
那么在这种的情况下，FaceView 的嘴巴始终是一条直线
I won't be smiling or frowning.
既不微笑也不伤心
And so this can be allowed to be nil.
所以 dataSource 可以允许是 nil
Okay, now normally, this is not going to want to be nil,
通常，我们不想让它是 nil
because we don't want a face with no frown and no smile.
因为我们不希望看到一个既不微笑也不伤心的脸
But, we'll certainly allow it.
我跟你们说的意思是，这里完全可以这么做（不提供 dataSource）
So, allow that there.
Now one other thing we have to do about this data source here
现在，我们还要继续对 dataSource 做的一件事情是
is we really want to describe it as weak.
声明它是一个 weak 类型的
Now this is gonna be the first time we talk about
这将成为我们讨论内存管理的第一堂课
memory management in this class.
And really the memory's just been
事实上，内存是被操作系统
managed automatically for you.
自动管理的，所以你不用担心
But here we have to be a little bit
但是我们需要注意的是
careful with the memory management of this pointer.
对这个指针的内存管理
Because, for example,
因为，例如
our controller is going to set itself as the data source.
我们的控制器将会设置它自身为 dataSource
So it's going to set this pointer back to itself because
然后它将设置这个指针为自身
our controller's going to be a FaceViewDataSource.
因为我们的控制器将会成为一个 FaceViewDataSource
And, unfortunately, the controller also has
不幸的是，我们的控制器
a pointer to this FaceView through the view hierarchy.
在视图的层次上已经有一个指向 FaceView 的指针了
Because it's gonna have some outlet to the face view, and
因为它有一个链接到 FaceView 的 outlet
so they'll be pointing to each other.
这样，这两个对象就互相指向了对方
And since they're pointing to each other they're keeping
那么在这个时候，它们
each other in memory at all times, so
就会一直在内存中相互引用对方，形成一个圈
that kinda memory cycle is really bad.
在内存中出现这样的圈是很可怕的
Because then the FaceView and
因为 FaceView
the controller can never leave memory.
和控制器都无法释放其的内存
They'll be stuck in memory forever.
它们就会永远呆在了内存中
So, by making this weak, if we put weak in front of a var
但是，通过在变量之前声明这个为 weak
pointer it means that this pointer, this thing, whatever
这个的意思是，这个对象，无论它
this points to, should not be used to keep it in memory.
指向的是什么东西，这个东西都不应该被用于在内存中保留它
So the controller is gonna set itself as this data source.
也就是说，控制器将会设置它自身为 dataSource
This pointer, since it is going to be a weak pointer,
这个指针，既然它声明了自己是一个 weak 指针
is not going to keep the controller in memory.
将不会在内存中保存这个控制器
So the controller will be allowed to go out of memory.
所以，这个控制器被允许从内存中释放
And when it goes out of memory,
当它被释放的时候
of course the FaceView loss will go out of
当然 FaceView 也会同样从内存中释放
memory with it because its entire view hierarchy,
因为 FaceView 在控制器的视图层次中
the controller's view hierarchy will go out as well.
而控制器的视图层次会随控制器一起被释放掉
And now you can see that we have an error here, okay?
现在你看到这里有一个错误
And this error says weak cannot be applied to non-class
这个错误说，weak 类型不能应用在非类的类型上
types, okay?
明白了吗？
So FaceViewDataSource is a protocol, not a class.
FaceViewDataSource 是一个协议，而不是一个类
So FaceViewDataSource could be an enum or
所以我们需要把 FaceViewDataSource 改成枚举类型
a struct and that's a problem because we really need this to
或者结构体，因为我们希望这个变量是 weak 类型的
be weak because we
我们不希望
don't want that cycle things pointing back to each other.
在内存中出现两个对象互相指向对方的环
So, we can actually make FaceViewDataSource, even
所以我们要讲 FaceViewDataSource
though it's a protocol, we can make it be a class type.
变成一个类，尽管它只是一个协议
If you remember from the slides in our
如果你还记得 Slide 中的
protocol declaration, we can say colon class.
协议声明的话，我们可以通过在协议后面加上 : class 来让它变成一个类
And that says that FaceViewDataSource can only be
这代表的是，FaceViewDataSource 只能被一个类所实现
implemented by a class, it cannot be implemented by
它不能被一个枚举类型或者一个结构体所实现
a struct or an enum, and that's perfectly fine and
这是完全没有问题的
usually that's what we're going to want anyway, but
同样也是我们所希望的
we definitely need that so we can have this weak behavior.
因为我们想让这个变量为 weak
So this data source, the pointer it has to whatever its
那么， 这个 dataSource，任何它指向的对象
data source will not keep it's data source in memory.
都不会被保存在 dataSource 的内存中了
As long as the dataSource is in memory,
只要是 dataSource 在内存中
this pointer will be good.
那么这个指针就不会有问题
As soon as the dataSource goes out of memory then this
一旦 dataSource 从内存中释放了
pointer will be set to nill automatically by the system.
那么这个指针将会被系统自动设成 nil
So it's pretty cool, these banners are pretty cool.
这非常酷
We don't use them a lot you saw that we used them for IB
平时我们不会经常使用到 weak，但是我们看到在 IBOutlet
outlets and this is the second place that we have used them,
里 weak 被大量使用到，这里
which is for delegation.
代理，是第二个被大量使用到的地方
We're always gonna use a weak var when we have delegation.
如果我们有一个代理的时候，我们始终需要一个 weak 类型的变量
Okay?
明白了吗？
That just requires that we make our protocol,
那仅仅要求我们使得 protocol，
you only work for classes.
只对 class 类型起作用。
All right?
明白了？
Okay? So now we
现在我们
have this nice data source right here.
有了个不错的 dataSource。
Let's go ahead and go to the next step,
我们继续到下一步，
which to use the data source to get our smiliness, right?
处理谁来使用这个 dataSource 得到 smiliness，对吗？
So we have our smiliness right here,
于是我们在这里得到了 smiliness，
it's currently at constant minus 0.5, so we're going to
现在是常量-0.5，所以我们要
get it from the data source by just saying to the data
从 dataSource 里获取，简单告诉 dataSource，
source, please give us our smiliness for FaceView Self.
请把 FaceView self 的 smiliness 给我们。
Okay?
Now when I type that in,
现在当我输入的时候，
Swift automatically put this question mark here.
Swift 自动把"?"放在这里。
I didn't type that.
我没有输入它。
It put it in here.
它把它放在这里。
Why did it put here?
为什么在这里？
Well it put it here because data source is an optional.
因为 dataSource 是 optional。
And it could be nil, okay?
它可能值为 nil，okay？
This is an optional, it could be nil.
这是个 optional，可以是 nil。
And so Swift is assuming that we wanna use optional
所以 Swift 假设我们想要在这里使用
chaining here.
optional 链。
And just, if this is nil, then this whole rest of
如果这是 nil，那么剩下所有的
this expression is gonna be ignored.
表达式都将被忽略。
This whole thing would be nil.
整体的值将是 nil。
And smiliness here would be set to nil, okay?
这里 smiliness 将会被设置为 nil，okay？
But smiliness, you can see this error here is
不过 smiliness，你会在这里看到这个 error
because smiliness, it can't be nil.
是因为 smiliness，它不能为 nil。
It has to be a double.
它必须是 double。
So we're going to use another cool little feature switch.
所以我们要使用另一个酷酷的小特性转换。
Swift which is the question mark question mark operator.
Swift 的 ?? 操作符。
Now what this operator says is,
这个操作符的意思是，
if the thing on the left-hand side of the question mark
如果操作符左侧的表达式
question mark is not nill, then use that.
不是 nil，那么以它为值。
But if it is nil, then use what's on the righthand side,
如果左侧表达式为 nil，那么使用右侧的表达式，
and to the right hand side I'm gonna put 0.0.
在右侧我放上0.0。
So what that says is that if the data source is nil,
它的意思是如果 dataSource 是 nil，
then we're going to use smiliness of 0,
那么我们将使用0为 smiliness 的值，
which is not a frown or a smile, it's in the middle.
它不是皱眉也不是微笑，它正好处在中间。
Now this is also gonna be working if
这也会在
smilinessForFaceView happens to return nil because you
smilinessForFaceView 正好返回 nil 时起作用
remember it is also an optional double right here.
因为你记得，它也是个 optinal double。
So that'll work perfectly fine there as well.
所以这里处理得非常好。
So whether this returns nil or
所以无论是这里返回 nil
whether this is nil, invalidating the rest of this,
还是这里是 nil，使得这里剩下的都无效，
we're gonna get no smile or frown.
我们将得不到笑脸或者皱眉。
So this is a cool little operator [INAUDIBLE].
所以这是个酷酷的小操作符。
Okay, so we've got our face view doing its part.
Okay，所以我们让 FaceView 干好了它的活。
It's declaring this nice property,
它在这里声明了这个漂亮的 property，
this protocol right here.
这个 protocol。
It's got a property which less people set themselves as
它有个让别人把他们设置为
the data source and
dataSource 然后
then it uses that data source to get its smiliness.
使用 dataSource 获得 smiliness 的 property。
All right, so
好了，所以
now let's go back to our happiness view controller.
现在让我们回到 HappinessViewController。
Okay? The controller has to
这个 controller 必须
implement the other side of delegation.
实现 delegation 的另一面。
Now you remember one of the steps it has is it has to
你们记住有一个步骤是，它必须
say to the world, I am HappinessViewController and
对世界宣布，我是 HappinessViewController
I implement the FaceViewDataSource protocol.
我会实现 FaceViewDataSource protocol。
And it does that by just saying FaceViewDataSource.
声明 FaceViewDataSource 就完成了这些。
Now as soon as I put this on here,
一旦我把它放在这里，
I'm going to get a warning right here,
我会得到一个 warning，
an error that says,
一个 error 说，
HappinessViewController does not conform to that protocol.
HappinessViewController 没有遵从那个 protocol.
And indeed it doesn't because we do not implement
实际上也没有，因为我们还没有
that smiliness by anywhere in our class.
在我们的 class 里实现 smiliness。
So, easily fixed though.
所以，简单地搞定它。
We go down here, now, since, we've already told it,
我们往下到这里，我们已经说过了，
it implements this.
它会实现这个。
If I just start typing smiliness it's going to
如果我开始输入 smiliness， 它会
automatically know to escape complete.
自动提示完成。
So I'll hit Tab.
所以我点击 Tab 键，
I've got my nice method here.
我就在这里得到了我的 method。
So how am I going to implement this protocol?
所以我如何实现这个 protocal？
Okay, this method in this protocol,
Okay，这个 protocol 的 method，
how am I going to implement that?
我怎么实现呢？
Well the happiness view controller is going to
好吧，HappinessViewController 要
interpret the happiness here.
在这里解析 happiness。
Which is the model.
这里是 model 层。
This is the happiness view controller's model.
这是 HappinessViewController 的 model。
It's gonna interpret this for the view, because the view
它要为 view 解析这些，因为 view
doesn't know about happiness, it only knows about smiliness.
不知道 happiness，它只知道 smiliness。
Smiliness goes from 1 to minus 1.
smiliness 的值介于-1到1之间。
Here, we're taking about the model which is happiness that
这里，我们讨论 model 层也就是 happiness，
goes from 0 to 100.
值介于0到100.
So it's a typical job of the controller to
所以这是个典型的 controller 的任务
interpret the model for the view.
为 view 解析 model。
You also interpret the view for the model and we'll see
你也会为了 model 解析 view，我们
that a little bit later when we talk about gestures.
待会儿讨论手势的时候再作说明。
But, here we're going to interpret the model for
但是，这里我们要解析 model 来
the view.
绘制 view。
So, I'm just going to return.
所以，我要返回。
Now, happiness is an int, and smiliness is a double, so
现在，happiness 是 int，smiliness 是 double，
I am going to have to convert the happiness.
所以我必须转化 happiness。
Also, the happiness is on a scale of 0 to 100, so
同样，happiness 是0到100之间的一个标量，
I am going to do minus 50.
所以我要减去50.
Divide by 50 to convert it into that plus 1 to
再除以50把它转化到
minus 1 scale.
1到-1之间。
So here I'm just interpreting the model for the view.
所以这里我刚刚为 view 解析了 model。
Make sense?
听懂了吗？
Now the last thing that needs to happen here is
现在这里最后一件事
that the controller needs to set itself
是 controller 需要把自己
as the data source of the FaceView.
设置为 FaceView 的 dataSource。
Let's all go back to FaceView,
让我们回到 FaceView，
I'm going to show you a nice trick here.
这里我要给你们展示一个技巧。
Cmd+Shift+O will let you type in like, start typing
Cmd+Shift+O 让你们这么输入，开始输入
FaceView and you can see it appear right there, and
"FaceView" 然后你会发现它出现在那，
you can switch really quick so Cmd+Shift+O is a great way to
你能非常快速地切换。所以 Cmd+Shift+O 是非常棒的
switch really quickly between files in your project.
在工程里快速切换文件的方式。
All right, so we need to set this data source right here
好了，我们需要在这里设置我们的 FaceView 的 dataSource
inside of our face view to be the controller.
为这个 controller。
So for the controller to do that,
所以 controller 为了做这些，
though, it needs to have a pointer to the FaceView.
它需要一个指向 FaceView 的 pointer。
And we do pointers to things in
我们在 view 里用 outlets
our view using outlets, right?
来实现指向事物的 pointer，对吗？
So let's go over here to our storyboard and wire up
所以我们来到 storyboard 这里
an outlet from this.
从这里引出一个 outlet。
We'll go to automatic mode up here.
我们来到 automatic 模式这里。
Remember, when you go to automatic mode you're
记住，当你进入 automatic 模式你会
gonna see the controller that matches what you
看到一些 controller
have selected in your storyboard.
这些 controller 跟你在 storyboard 里选择的控件有关。
So here we can have that.
所以这里我们能看到它。
So I'm just going to take my controller right here and
所以我要在这里选择我的 controller
I'm going to Ctrl+drag to create an outlet.
同时 Ctrl+拖拽 创建一个 outlet。
This is the same way that I create an outlet to buttons or
这种方式和为 button 或者
to the labels or whatever we've done.
label 创建 outlet 的方式一摸一样。
It's exactly the same.
完全一样。
It's just a normal outlet.
这是个普通的 outlet。
I'm going to call it Face View.
我把它命名为 faceView
So here's really nice FaceView right there.
于是那里有个不错的 Faceview。
Now where in my code should I go and
现在我在代码的哪里
set this var right here?
设置这个变量呢？
Okay, this data source var.
Okay，这个 dataSource 变量。
Well a great place to do it since this is
好吧，一个合理的位置 (既然这是那个
the faceView we want to set that in,
要被设置的 faceView）
is right here in the property observer for the FaceView.
就是在这里，FaceView 的 property observer。
This property observer is called when the iOS starts up
这个 property observer 会在 iOS 启动
and loads the story board.
并加载这个 storyboard 时调用。
It connects this outlet.
它连接这个 outlet。
It's going to set this variable.
然后设置这个变量。
And so it's a perfect time when this is
所以这是个完美的时刻
being set to go ahead and
当这个变量被设置继续前行
say FaceView.dataSource equals self, okay?
然后设置 faceView.dataSource = self, okay?
This is the controller.
这是 controller。
It's perfectly legal for
对它来说这么干完全合法，
it to say this because it is a FaceView data source, right?
因为它是 FaceView 的 dataSource，对吗？
The happiness view controller is a face view data source so
HappinessViewController 是 FaceView 的 dataSource
we can say that it is the new source.
所以我们说它是新的来源。
It's perfectly fine equals.
它是非常好的等价物。
All right?
对吗？
That make sense that we're doing that?
明白我们这么做的意义了吗？
Okay, so now everything is hooked,
Okay，现在一切都组装好了，
and how is this gonna work.
这是怎么工作的。
It's going to be very straight forward.
非常直接。
Every time that the face redraws itself,
每次 face 重绘自身的时候，
it's going to look for its data source.
它会去查找自己的 dataSource。
Which we have set right here in our controller to
也就是我们在 controller 这里设置的
be the controller itself.
controller 自身。
It's going to get its smiliness from the data
它会从 dataSource
source by calling the method in the protocol up here, okay?
通过调用上面 protocol 里的 method， 来获得 smiliness，okay？
We implement that method in our controller.
我们在 controller 里实现了对应的 method。
We interpret the model for the view.
我们为 view 解析 model。
And the FaceView's gonna be able to draw the proper value.
然后 FaceView 就会绘制出用合适的值。
Now there's only one other thing that I wanna do here.
现在这里只剩下一件我要做的事了。
Which is every time something changes our model,
也就是每次我们的model变动时，
I wanna make sure the face redraws itself.
我要让 face 重新绘制自身。
Of course, because we're representing that in the face.
这是当然的，因为我们要在 face 中表现出来。
So the best space to do that is in this update UI, so
所以做这个的最佳的位置是 UpdateUI
every single time the happiness changes I'm going to
每一次 happiness 值变动了
ask my faceView to set needs display of itself.
我都会让 faceView 设置 setNeedsDisplay.
In other words, to redraw.
换句话说，重绘。
Remember set needs display is the thing you do that says
记住，setNeedsDisplay 就是那种
hey, call my draw rect, redraw me.
“hey，调用我的 drawRect 函数，重绘我”的意思
Now if I didn't do this then every time I
现在如果我没有做这个，那么每次
set my happiness the FaceView would not draw, okay?
我设置 happiness， faceView都不会重新绘制，okay？
Now maybe if I rotated my device and
现在可能是因为我旋转了我的设备
it redrew then it would show it but.
然后它重新绘制显示出来了。
Otherwise it wasn't gonna show it.
否则它不会显示出来。
We've got this hooked up, it really should be the happiness
我们把这个关联上了，它应该是真正的
that's showing in here rather than the smiliness.
显示在这里的 happiness 而不是 smiliness。
So it shouldn't be a flat line right here,
所以它不该是这样一条水平的线段。
it should actually show the happiness.
它应该实际展示 happiness。
Let's go ahead run, see what we got here.
我们运行一下，看看效果如何。
I knew we should get a happiness of 75,
我们应该得到一个75的 happiness。
which is a little bit happy.
有一点点的 happy。
Yeah. That looks good right there.
好的。看上去挺不错。
Let's go change our happiness here to be sad, like maybe 10.
我们把 happiness 改成悲伤，比如说10.
Go ahead and re-run.
重新运行。
Okay, we're sad, all right and
Okay，我们是悲伤的，好了
let's go to the ecstatic and we're ecstatic, okay?
我们展示一下狂喜，我们是狂喜的，okay？
Or we should be ecstatic because we
或者我们应该是狂喜的，因为
successfully implemented delegation.
我们成功地实现了 delegation。
>> All right.
Let's go back to our slides and
我们回到课件上
cover the next thing here, which is gestures.
讨论下一个东西，手势。
All right.
So we know how to draw inner view,
所以我们知道怎么去绘制内部 view，
now we wanna handle these gestures.
现在我们要处理这些手势。
Okay?
You know, pinches and maybe rotations, swipes, taps,
比如，pinchs，rotations，swipes，taps
things like that.
等手势。
Now we could get the raw data about every finger that
我们可以获取到每个手指按下、
goes down, and where it is, that data is available, but
位置的原始信息，
we never look at that.
但是我们很少直接使用这些信息。
First of all it's very difficult to
因为我们自己通过这些原始信息
look at that raw data, and
很难判断
see, is this a swipe, or is it just moving over to the right.
这是一个swipe手势，还是单纯向右滑动。
So iOS does all that for
不过 iOS 为我们做了底层封装，
you, and that's the only way I'm going to teach you
而本课上，我只会教你
to react to user touches is via gestures, okay?
通过手势来处理用户的触摸事件，明白吗？
So how do gestures work?
那么手势是如何工作的呢？
Gestures are recognized by UI views when
当手指在视图边界内滑动时，
the gesture happens inside their bounds.
视图会识别特定的手势。
Okay, I told you the views are rectangular areas where you
是的，我说过，视图是用来绘制和
draw and you recognize gestures so
识别手势的矩形区域
this is how it happens.
手势就是这样被识别的。
There's a class called UIGestureRecognizer.
有一个叫UIGestureRecognizer的类。
It's an abstract base class.
它是一个抽象类。
You never actually create a UIGestureRecognizer base
通常，你不会直接创建UIGestureRecognizer基类，
class, you create a sub class of UIGestureRecognizer.
而是创建它的子类。
And those subclasses are concrete in
因为这些具体的子类
that they know about certain gestures, swipes and pans and
能够识别特定的手势，比如swipes、pans、touch
touches, et cetera.
等。
So there are two sides to using a gesture recognizer.
使用手势识别器有两个步骤。
One is you have to add a gesture recognizer to a view.
首先是为视图添加手势识别器。
That says to the view, start recognizing this gesture.
这表示，该视图现在能识别手势。
If you recognize this gesture, you let somebody know.
如果你识别了这个手势，就报告给某个对象。
Okay?
明白吗？
And you do that with
完成这个步骤，
a function on UIView called add gesture recognizer.
你只需要调用视图的addGestureRecognized方法。
Couldn't be simpler.
非常简单。
Then the second piece, though, is when you create the gesture
第二步是，当你创建手势识别器的时候，
recognizer, you have to say, if you recognize the gesture,
你必须指定一个对象，如果视图识别了这个手势
who are you gonna tell about it?
就报告给这个对象。
Okay, you have to notify somebody and
是的，你需要让某个对象知道
say oh, I recognize that swipe.
嘿，这是一个swipe手势。
Okay?
明白吗？
So there's the handler.
也就是说，你需要提供一个处理事件的对象。
So you've got the recognizer, that's the view.
一个是识别手势的对象，就是视图。
Okay, the gesture recognizer in association with the view.
是的，添加了手势识别器的视图。
And then you've got the handler that's who handles it,
然后是处理事件的对象，
and those are not always the same person.
这两个并不一定是同一个对象。
Sometimes they're the same object, sometimes not.
有些时候是的，有些时候不是。
Usually the first one, adding a gesture recognizer to
通常，为视图添加识别器
a view is done by a controller.
是通过控制器来完成的。
Although a view will sometimes add it to itself, for
不过有些时候，视图自己也可以添加识别器，
example scroll view.
比如scroll view。
Scroll view doesn't even exist without the pan and
scroll view 可以自动识别
pinch gestures, that's what it does.
pan和pinch手势。
So it adds the gesture recognizers to itself.
它为自身添加了这些识别器。
But a lot of times other times you have a gesture that
但是大多数时候，
you're going to recognize only if the controller wants you to
只有在控制器需要视图识别手势的时候，
recognize it, so
你才添加识别器到视图上，
you make some public handler possibly in your view.
你可能在视图中 实现公开的事件处理方法。
And then your controller can add this gesture recognizer to
然后控制器可以添加识别器到
one of its views, one of its minions and say,
视图，
start recognizing this gesture and you can even handle it
视图开始识别手势，甚至在手势被识别后
yourself if you want, the controller might say.
可以自己处理相关事件。
Or the controller might say oh, and I'll handle it.
又或者由控制器来处理。
So the second thing, the handling is either done by
所以，第二步中，如果是显示相关的事件
the view if it's a display-oriented handling
一般由视图自己来处理，
thing, or it's done by the controller if it's handling
而如果涉及到修改model的时候
something that's going to modify the model.
事件一般由控制器来处理。
Okay? Or be something that's
明白吗？ 如果
complicated that's going to cause multiple views to
涉及很多视图这种复杂情况的时候
be involved and so the controller has to do it.
就必须由控制器来处理了。
And it's perfectly fine to have either the controller or
所以，事件的处理通常都是由控制器
the view handle something although you would
或者视图两个中的一个来完成的，
never have the view handle a gesture that is directly
你绝不会在视图中直接
modifying the model cuz a view can't see the model.
修改model，因为model对view是不可见的。
Only a controller can do that.
只有控制器可以直接和model交互。
Okay?
明白吗？
So how do you add a gesture recognizer to a UI view?
那么，怎样为视图添加识别器呢？
It's very simple.
非常简单。
I'm going to do it in a way that is very common, which is
我会用一种很通用的方式，
to do it in the property observer of an outlet setter,
就是在属性监听的set方法中来完成，
just exactly like we did when we set the face views delegate
就和我们在设置face view代理一样
in the property observer, when the face view got set.
当face view调用set方法时，我们为它设置代理。
We could do the same thing adding adjuster recognizer.
我们可以通过同样的方法来添加手势识别器。
In fact, we're going to do that in the demo.
事实上，我们会在demo中演示这个过程。
So here I have an IV outlet.
这里我有一个IBOutlet属性。
It's just a UI view.
就是一个
In my story board.
storyboard中的视图。
It's called pannableView and
它叫pannableView
I'm going to make it so it can pan around in there.
我希望可以拖动这个视图。
All right, and in his property observer there the did stat.
好的，在这个属性监听器的didSet方法中。
I'm going to add this gesture recognizer.
我将添加这个识别器。
I'm going to create a pan gesture recognizer and
我需要创建pan手势识别器，
then add it to the view.
然后添加到视图中。
So here I'm creating it.
这里我创建它。
This is just
我只需要
calling UIPanGestureRecognizer initializer here.
调用UIPanGestureRecognizer的初始化方法即可。
The arguments to the initializer are who to
第一个参数表示，当手势被识别的时候，
send a message to when the gesture is recognized.
向谁发送消息。
When we start seeing a pan.
当视图识别到pan手势。
And as the pan is happening we're gonna be
我们会向这个对象
sending a message to this object.
发送一个消息。
In this case it's self.
这里，它是self。
So this method would obviously be in a controller, right?
所以这个方法肯定在一个控制器中，不是吗？
Because controllers are the only
因为只有
things that have the outlets.
控制器才会有outlets。
So this thing's going to be
所以这里
handled by the controller itself.
会由控制器来处理。
And then action is the name of the method.
action参数表示事件处理的方法名称。
It's just a string that is the name of
就是方法名称字符串，
the method that's gonna be
当手势被识别的时候，
called in the controller when this gesture is recognized.
会调用控制器中的这个方法。
Now notice there's a little colon on the end there?
看见后面的冒号了吗？
That means that it's called a, it's gonna
这表示
call a method called pan that has an argument.
这个pan方法会有一个参数。
That's what the colon means.
这就是冒号的意思。
There's an argument there.
表示方法需要一个参数。
Okay, now you don't have to have the colon there if
你也可以不添加冒号
you want, but if you don't have it there, then you
如果没有冒号，那么pan被调用的时候
won't get the argument when pan gets called and
你就得不到这个参数
the argument you get is the gesture recognizer.
而这个参数就是GestureRecognizer
And for something like pan where you're gonna try and
有时候你需要
figure out where the finger is,
判断手指的点击位置，
you need the gesture recognizer so
这样你就必须得到这个参数
it can tell you where the finger is basically, okay?
来判断手指的触点在哪里。
So we almost always have a colon.
因此，我们通常都有冒号。
The only place you
只有在
wouldn't have a colon might be like a swipe.
使用swipe手势的时候你不需要冒号。
Because the swipe just got recognized,
因为这就是一个swipe手势，
you don't really need any information,
你不需要额外的信息来判断，
you just need to know what happened.
你只需要确定这是一个swipe手势。
So you might have action, quote, handle swipe, no colon.
所以你只需要在双引号中加上方法名称即可，不需要冒号。
Then we just ask the view,
然后，
this panable view, please recognize this gesture when it
当一个pan手势发生在视图边界的时候，
happens inside your bounds.
这个视图就可以识别这个手势了。
Okay that's simple, that's like turning on,
就是这么简单，就像打开开关，
this is the on switch, for
比如switch控件，
turning on that pan gesture I recognized,
可以通过pan手势
by asking some of you to recognize it.
来切换状态。
So now every time this view recognizes a pan going on
每次视图在边界内识别了pan手势的时候
inside its bounce it's going to send the message pan
它就会向控制器发送带一个参数的
with an argument to the controller.
pan消息。
Everybody okay with this?
都明白了吗？
This is how you set up a gesture recognizer.
这是配置手势识别器的方法。
How about the handler?
那么如何处理事件呢？
So that pan thing with that argument, how do we do that?
有了这个参数后，我们可以做哪些事情呢？
For us to handle the pan we need information about
在处理pan手势的时候，我们需要
what's going on in that pan.
知道它的一些信息。
Where are the fingers moving?
比如手指移动到哪里了？
We need to know about that.
我们需要知道这些。
So the concrete subclasses of UI gesture recognizer like UI
UIGestureRecognizer的子类，比如
pangesture recognizer, they add methods that
PanGestureRecognizer，他们针对特定的手势
are specific to whatever kind of gesture they are.
添加了自己特定的方法。
So the panGesture one has a translation in
比如PanGesture就有translationInView方法，
view which tells you how far the finger has moved since,
用来告诉你 从手势被识别或重置开始
either since the panGesture was first recognized, or
手指移动了多远的
since that last got reset.
距离。
And you can reset with this set translation which will
你可以通过setTranslation方法
reset this translation to a different spot so
重置这个起点
that the next time that you get notified,
这样下一次计算拖动距离的时候
it will be the distance between this.
会以你重置的起点开始计算。
So that's a good way to get incremental panning instead of
这是一个得到增加距离的好方法
just the total distance that you've panned.
而不仅仅是得到总距离。
And then also I can tell you velocity,
还可以得到velocity（速度）
how fast are you panning around?
拖动的速度有多快？
Is the person kinda moving real slow, or
用户可能拖动得很慢，或者是想
trying to put something in a perfect spot,
拖动到某个特定的点，
or are they kind of zooming it around, okay,
又或者是在放大缩小等，
you might react differently depending on the velocity.
你可能对不同的速度做出不同的反应。
So those are the things that are very specific to Pan, so
这是pan手势的一些特有的东西，也是为什么
that's why these methods are in panGesture Recognizer.
这些方法属于PanGestureRecognizer。
Now that last one is interesting because of
最后一个是incremental translation，
this incremental translation.
这个很有趣。
A lot of people really don't quite understand this.
因为大多数人不是很理解这个。
But you'll see when we do the demo, we'll
但是在做demo的时候你会明白的，
do incremental translation with our pinch gesture.
我们会在pinch手势中演示incremental translation。
And it'll make a little more sense what's going on there.
那时候你就更容易理解它了。
The abstract superclass UIGestureRecognizer.
抽象类UIGestureRecognizer
It also has a very important property called State.
有个很重要的属性 叫state（状态）。
Okay when you have a pan it actually goes through states.
pan手势会经历许多个状态。
It starts out in the state Possible.
首先是Possible状态。
It's possible a pan can happen.
表示它或许是一个pan手势。
Then if it were a swipe or
然后如果手势是扫动或者
a discrete gesture, you would just get one state.
非连续类型的，就会变为另一个状态。
Which is I recognize this.
就是Recognized状态。
So that's Recognized.
表示手势被识别了。
But if it's pan and
但是如果是pan手势
continuous, then you're gonna get began.
即手势连续的，state状态就会变为Began状态。
Okay, recognize that the pan has started.
明白吗，表示pan手势开始识别了。
You'll get that.
就是这样。
And then every time the finger moves,
随着手指的移动，
you're gonna get another call to your handler saying,
会不断通知事件处理对象
changed, changed, changed.
状态改变为Changed了。
And then when the finger goes up,
当手指离开屏幕的时候，
you'll get another one that says the state is now ended.
状态就变为Ended。
So this is basically a little state machine.
这就像一个时间机器。
Obviously a pan goes through the state machine of possible,
pan手势在不同的时刻有不同的状态。
began, changed, ended.
开始，改变，结束。
All right?
明白吗？
There's also failed and
也有Failed和Canceled状态，
canceled, like you're in the middle of a pan and
比如在pan手势的中途
a phone call comes in, okay?
一个电话打进来了，明白吗？
That's going to cancel that pan, alright?
这样这个pan手势就会被取消掉，知道吗？
So sometimes you have to pay attention to cancellation like
所以有时你需要注意手势的取消状态
that and sometimes not, it all depends on what you're doing
就像刚才这种情况，而有时候不必，
with your pan, sometimes your pan is updating.
这全由pan手势的当前状态决定，有时候，pan正在更新。
Whatever's there is in real time and
无论状态机当前处于什么状态
if the phone call comes in it just stops doing that and
如果有电话打入，状态机将暂停原有操作，
it's fine, everything is in perfectly fine state.
没问题，一切都处于正常的状态。
Other times it might be putting something in
有时候，pan手势会将一些东西
some temporary state and
放入在临时状态中
now it's interrupted it's gotta clean up, or something.
当该手势被中断的时候，临时状态中得数据将被清空，或者做一些其他操作
All right. So given this information,
好，有了这些信息，
what would the pan handler look like?
那pan手势控制器到底是如何实现呢？
Okay? The pan
pan手势控制器
handler would be a method called pan.
是一个名叫 pan 的方法。
It would take one argument which is
该 方法带有一个参数
the UIPanGestureRecognizer itself.
即，UIPanGestureRecognizer本身。
You can see right there.
在这里你可以看到
Okay?
We're going to look at the state machine and
我们来看一下状态机，
say what state it's in.
状态机处于什么样的状态。
So in my pan,
在pan手势中
I'm only going to do something when the gesture moves or
当手势移动或者手指上划，
the finger goes up.
我只需要稍微做一点点事
I'm not even gonna do anything when it first goes down.
当它第一次下划的时候，我不需要做任何事。
I can choose which things I wanna do.
我可以选择，我想要的操作
But that's what I wanna do.
这些就是我想做的。
Hopefully you know about fall through.
愿你们对fall through有所了解
You read that in the documentation.
你在文档中查阅过相关内容
Fall through is just a thing in switch that says
Fall through 是在 switch 中用于
the implementation of this case is to go to the next one.
说明当前case的函数实现，即为下一个case的函数实现
And do whatever the next one is, okay?
无论下一个case的实现是什么。
So it just falls through to the next case.
所以，它就落到了下一个case.
So in changed and
在changed
ended, I'm gonna do exactly the same thing.
和ended中，我想执行相同的函数。
What I'm gonna do is I'm gonna find out where
我要做的就是
the pan is in the coordinates of the panable view, so
在可拖动view的坐标系中，找出pan手势的位置
its coordinate system.
pan手势所在的坐标系
'Kay, that's translation in view.
好，那就是pan手势在view中的坐标
I give it the view.
我在view中得到这个坐标值
I want the coordinate system.
我需要坐标系
It's gonna give me the point in that view where the pan is.
它将告诉我，在view中pan手势所在的点的位置
Then I'm gonna update anything I want inside of my controller
然后，我将更新控制器中我所需的东西
cuz this is being handled by the controller.
因为这就是由控制器来控制的
So I'm gonna update anything I want based on that
所以，我要，基于x,y坐标轴，来更新任何我所需要的东西，
translation, x and y, then I'm gonna reset the translation
然后，再重置坐标，
and I don't have to do this but I'm going to in this case,
我并非每次都必须执行这一步，只是需要在这种情况下执行，
reset the translation back to 0, so
将坐标重置为0，
that the next time I get this called, in the next time it
所以，当下一次调用这个方法的时候，即下一次手势状态
changes it's gonna be just the difference.
改变的时候，将得到当前位置与上一次位置之间的偏差
Otherwise it's going to tell me from the time the gesture
在其他情况下，将得到第一次识别到手势
was first recognized to where I am now.
到当前时间的时间差
So that'd be a big distance when I
当我移动的时候，我只想知道增加的距离
just want the incremental distance as I move around.
这有可能是一个很远的距离
So that set translation to 0 is optional,
所以将坐标设置为0是可选的
you can do it if you want.
如果你想做的话，可以做。
Okay? So that's it.
就这些
That's how we handle a gesture.
这是如何控制一个手势
Very straight forward.
非常直白
So let's talk about some of
我们来讨论一下，当前存在的几个
the concrete gestures that exist.
具体的手势。
There's pinch.
有缩放(pinch)手势
Okay? Pinch,
instead of giving you translation,
pinch手势给你传递的不是坐标
it gives you scale.
而是比例
So when the pinch starts, the scale is 1.
当pinch手势开始的时候，比例为1
If you spread your fingers out twice as wide,
如果你把你的手指拉宽两倍
the scale would be 2.
比例将变成2
If you go down to half as wide, the scale would be 0.5.
如果你将手指靠拢到一半的位置，比例将变成0.5
Okay?
So that's how pinches work.
这就是pinch手势的工作原理
And it'll tell you the velocity.
它也会告诉你速度
How fast the person is pinching.
用户缩放的速度有多快
There's also rotation.
还有旋转(rotation)手势
So that's a two finger thing as well.
这也是一个两个手指的手势
You turn in a circle.
你转一个圈
So it's like you're turning a knob.
就像在转动一个旋钮
It tells you how many radians the thing has been rotated.
它会告诉你，该物体旋转了多少弧度
Okay?
And it'll also tell you how fast in
它也会告诉你，旋转的过程中
radians per second the rotations happen.
每秒转动的弧度
So that's the way you can rotate.
这就是你旋转的方式
There's also swipes.
接下来是滑动(swipes)手势
Now, swipes are a little different.
现在，swipes手势有一些不同
When you create the swipe gesture, okay,
当你创建一个swipes手势的时候，
back in the property observer of the outlet,
返回到outlet的property observer中
I created a pan gesture.
我创建了一个pan手势
But if I created a swipe gesture there,
但如果我创建了一个swipe手势
I would send a message,
我将发送一条消息
set the property of the swipe gesture,
来设置swipe手势的属性，
number of touches required, or swipe direction there, and
点击所需的次数，或者滑动的方向
that determines whether it's a two finger swipe to the left
这也决定了是两个手指向左滑动，
or a one finger swipe down, or whatever.
还是一个手指向下滑动，或者其他什么。
You just kinda say what kind of swipe you're looking for,
你只需要说明你在查找的滑动类型
and then your handler would only be called once,
在状态为.Recognized的情况下，
with the state .Recognized when that combination
一旦手指合并，且向指定方向滑动，
of fingers and direction happens.
控制器将会被调用
So that's a little different than these other ones.
所以，这里与其他的有些不同
And there's also tap, a question.
接下来是点击(Tap)手势，有问题。
>> Also for these gestures I said you can now test in
>> 对于这些手势，我想说，你现在可以在
the simulator, right?
模拟器中测试，对嘛？
>> Can you test these in the simulator?
>> 你可以在模拟器中，测试这些手势吗？
Absolutely you can test these in
你当然可以在模拟器中测试这些手势，
the simulator, I'll show you.
我将会展示给你们看。
>> How do you test more than one finger?
>> 你要如何测试多于一个手指的手势呢？
>> Yes, how do you test more than one finger in
>> 对，你要如何在模拟器中测试多于一个手指的手势
the simulator, I'll show you how to do that.
我将会给你们展示，这个手势的操作方法。
Tap gesture is an interesting one.
点击（Tap）手势是比较有趣的手势之一。
It seems like it would be
这个手势看起来似乎是
discrete because it's kind of like swipe.
间断的，因为这类似于滑动（swipe）手势。
You set up the number of taps and the number of touches.
你可以设置点击(tap)和触摸(touch)的次数
Except for that if you have a double tap it'll actually tell
除此之外，如果你双击，事实上它会告诉
you about the first tap and the second tap.
你第一次的点击和第二次的点击。
So if you're only interested in the actual double tap you
所以，如果你需要知道双击
can just look at the state ending because
你可以只关注结束的状态
that's the end of that gesture.
因为那是该手势的结尾
But if you want to look at the intermediate states you
但如果你想要关注中间状态
can actually look at the dot changed stated as well, so
实际上，你也可以查看点改变的状态
it's not purely a discrete gesture tap.
所以这并不是一个真正的分离手势
Okay, so let's go look at how we do gestures by putting some
好，一起来看一下，我们应该如何为
gestures in the FaceView.
FaceView添加手势
So I'm gonna put two gestures in.
我要添加两个手势
I'm gonna put in pinch to change the size of the face,
添加pinch手势来改变脸的大小
and then I'm gonna put in pan to control the happiness,
然后，添加pan手势来控制表情
in other words, control my model.
换句话说，控制我的模型
All right?
With pan.
用pan手势
When I move up and
当我上下拖动，
down it's gonna be happy is up, sad is down.
向上拖动时，是开心的表情；向下拖动时，是悲伤的表情。
Not a swipe but actual pan so
不是滑动，而是拖动
I can move my happiness up in small increments if I want.
所以，如果我想的话，我也可以将这个表情向上移动一点
All right, so let's go back to here to do that.
好，让我们继续。
So let's go get some more space here.
让我们腾出更多的空间
So we'll go here.
从这里开始
So we'll do the pinch first.
我们先来完成这个pinch手势
Let's do the pinch first.
先做pinch手势
So the first thing I'm gonna do when I
当我添加pinch手势的时候，我要做的第一件事
make my pinch happen is to add a gesture recognizer.
添加一个手势识别器
A pinch gesture recognizer to my FaceView.
针对FaceView的pinch手势识别器
And so a great place to do that,
添加这个方法的位置
as I said, is in the property observer of the FaceView.
正如我所说，就是在FaceView的Property Observer中
So here I can just say, add gesture.
所以，这里我只需要写addGesture
Whoops, sorry, FaceView.
抱歉，FaceView
FaceView.
Add gesture recognizer.
AddGestureRecognizer.
And this is just any kind of gesture recognizer.
这是任意类型的手势识别器
I'm going to do a pan Gesture.
而我要做的是pan手势
So I'm going to say UI Pan gesture recognizer.
所以，我要写 UIPanGestureRecognizer
And then you can see that it
你可以看到
has target in action are the arguments.
action中的target是参数
So the target I'm gonna have the pinch be handled
entirely by the view.
Because all it's doing is changing the view scale.
因为手势的所有操作，都是在改变view的比例
Its own scale.
view本身的比例
So there's no reason I'm the controller I don't need to
毫无疑问，controller没有必要
get involved with that.
涉及动作
So I'm just going to have the target be the FaceView.
所以，我只需要将FaceView传给target
So the FaceView is going to handle this pan.
由FaceView处理pan
Or, sorry, we're doing pan, no, we'll do pinch.
抱歉，我们正在写pan手势,我们本来要做pinch手势的
So I'm doing pinch.
我正在做pinch手势
Your pinch first.
先做pinch手势
So we're doing pinch.
正在做pinch手势
So we're doing the pinch of scale, not pan, sorry.
我们正在做比例的缩放，并不是pan，抱歉
We're doing the pinch and I'm gonna have the FaceView
我们在做pinch手势，我将要用FaceView
handle this because it's just gonna modify its scale.
来控制pinch手势，因为它仅仅改变了FaceView的比例
And this action needs to be some nonprivate method
对于action，在FaceView中，需要一个非私有的方法
in my FaceView that I can call to handle it.
用来调用这个函数。
So, let's go ahead and go over to our faceview and
继续，到faceview
add such a thing.
添加这样的一个东西
So I'm going to call this method, what to call it?
我要调用这个方法，那么，谁来调用它？
Scale.
Okay?
And it's going to take a UI pinch gesture recognizer
它将把UIPinchGestureRecognizer
as an argument, and we'll call that the gesture.
作为参数，我们将使用这个手势。
And all this is gonna do is modify our scale.
所有的这些，都是用来调整比例大小的
Okay?
Understand? You got this method here?
明白吗？都理解这个方法了吗？
So how is this method gonna do this?
那么，这个方法将要做些什么呢？
Well, I'm only going to adjust my scale when the pinch moves.
好，pinch的时候，我只是在调整比例
I'm not gonna do it when it first goes down because it's
当手指第一次点击到屏幕的时候，我无需执行这个方法
gonna be scale of 1 anyway, and
因为此时无论如何它的比例都将是1
I probably should do it when the fingers go up, but just to
当手指移开的时候，我应该要执行这个方法，但是
make less code here I'm just gonna do it when it changes.
这里尽可能少写一点代码，因为我只想在手势改变的时候执行
So I'm gonna say if the gesture state equals .changed.
所以，我会写如果手势的状态等于 .changed
Okay.
Then I'm going to take my own scale and
然后，我将用原来的比例(scale)
multiply it by the gestures scale.
乘以手势的比例(gesture.scale)
Okay.
So if the gesture pinch scales out.
如果手势向外拉伸
I'm going to make my scale bigger.
将使得比例增大
If it scales in I'm going to make my scale smaller.
如果手势向内靠拢，将使得比例缩小
Okay.
And I'm going to reset the gesture scale back to 1
我要把手势的比例(gesture.scale)重置为1
all the time.
任何情况下
By resetting it back to 1 then I'm only getting the
通过将比例重置为1，我才能只获取到
difference between the last time it told me to update.
用于更新的最后一次变化的比例大小
So that way I can update my scale every time it moves.
每当手势移动的时候，我将会更新比例
And since I keep resetting back to one,
再将比例重置为1
I keep getting incremental scale.
我一直获取增加的比例
It's gonna keep making my scale bigger or
根据最后一次
smaller depending on whether the last movement of
缩放的情况
the pinch was bigger or smaller.
使得比例变大或者变小
This makes my code a lot simpler.
这使得代码简洁很多
So that's it. That's all that's necessary.
就是这些，这就是所有必需的代码
And it's typical for gesture recognizers to be this simple,
一个典型的手势识别器的代码就是如此简单
to not require a lot of code.
不需要编写一大堆的代码
So, this is the name of the handler.
所以 scale 是 handler 的名称
So, let's go back to our controller and
让我们回到控制器的代码
put that in here, the action is scale.
把手势识别器的 action 设置为 scale
And it did take that argument.
由于这是其中的一个参数
So, I do need to put the colon there.
所以我需要在 scale 后面加上一个冒号
Okay, and that's it.
完成了
That's all that's required.
所有所需的代码我们都完成了
So, let's go ahead and try it.
让我们运行一下来看看
Now as was being asked here, how do I do two fingers,
这里我经常被问到的一个问题就是，如何我模拟两个手指的操作
I only got one mouse here.
我只有一个鼠标
And the answer is you hold down the option key.
回答是，你按住 option 键
You see when you hold down option, you get two fingers.
当你按住 option 键时，你模拟了两个手指的操作
Okay, and they're evenly spaced from the middle, and
没有问题吧？这两个手指与中心相对称
I can use them to pinch in and out.
我能使用这两个手指来模拟缩放的操作
Okay, there we go.
让我们继续
So you can see adding gestures really, really simple, okay.
你可以通过上面的演示看到，添加一个手势识别器是非常简单的
You can do other things too.
当然你也可以做其他的事情
If I can remember here I think Cmd, what is it.
可能是 ⌘ 键吧，我记得
There's other things too,
用鼠标模拟其他的手指操作
I can't remember offhand what they are but
我现在记不起来了，但是
you can take the two things and move them.
你可以模拟两指移动
There we go. I'm using Shift.
噢，就是这个，按住 Control 键的同时，按住 Shift 键
Now you can move them up here.
现在你可以用鼠标模拟两个手指同时上移
So that you can expand them out from here or whatever.
你可以模拟把这个图形扩展开或者其他的什么操作
So you can control them a little bit.
但是你只能用鼠标模拟一点点的手指动作
Only two, you can't do three fingers or whatever.
因为你只能模拟两个手指的动作，不能模拟两个手指以上的动作
So there's some limitations but
尽管有些局限性
you can do some stuff there, all right.
但是至少你能在模拟器里模拟一些手指动作，明白了吗？
So that's good. So
很好
now let's talk about another gesture.
让我们继续讲一下其他的手势
Let's do a pan gesture, where
让我们来做一个拖动手势识别器（Pan Gesture）
if I pan up it's gonna make my guy happier and
当我向上拖动的时候，我希望让我们的小人看上去比较开心
if I pan down it's gonna make him sadder.
当我向下拖动的时候，我希望让我们的小人看上去比较难过
Okay.
没问题吧？
So I can use a pan gesture for that.
我可以使用一个拖动手势识别器来实现
Now, I could just go right here and
我在这个 faceView 里添加与之前 Pinch Gesture 类似的代码
do the same thing, I could say faceView.addGestureRecognizer-
这里我输入 faceView.addGestureRecognizer
(UIPanGestureRecognizer{target .
UIPanGestureRecognizer(target: ...
The target would be myself.
target 将会是 self
Because if I'm modifying the model with that pan gesture,
因为我通过这个拖动手势识别器改变了我的 Model
my view can't do that.
我的 View 不能够完成这些
The controller has to handle it itself.
必须由控制器来处理
And we can have the action of
然后我们可以把这样的一个 Action
this thing be something like changeHappiness.
称之为 changeHappiness
Take that argument or something.
接受一个参数或者是其他什么的东西
So I could do this.
我可以按照之前我所说的这么做
But I'm not gonna do it this way, okay.
但我不想这么做，好吗？
This would be perfectly fine.
我这么写，一点问题都没有
But I'm gonna show you how
但是我想演示给你们
you can set up gestures in the storyboard.
如何在 Storyboard 中添加手势识别器
So you don't even need this line of code, okay.
所以你甚至都不需要这段代码
So here's how that works.
接下来看好
We're gonna go over here.
我们点击这里
Let's get our storyboard.
点击我们的 Main.storyboard
And I wanna add a gesture recognizer to this view.
我想在这个视图之上添加一个手势识别器
I do it by going over here,
我先点击这里
same place where I add things to my view here.
在我向我的视图添加控件的这个地方
If you go down towards the bottom,
如果你向下滚动
you'll see that there's tap gesture, pinch gesture,
你会看到里面有单击（Tap）、缩放（Pinch）
rotation gesture, swipe gesture, pan gesture.
旋转（Rotation）、滑动（Swipe）、拖动（Pan）的手势识别器
Okay.
So I'm gonna grab this pan gesture and drop it on this
我这里拖动这个拖动手势识别器并将其放在
view, which says I want this view to recognize a pan.
这个视图之上，这也就表示我希望这个视图识别一个拖动手势
Now you might say, whoa, where'd that go?
现在你可能会问，这个识别器去哪里了？
I didn't see anything there what's going on?
我没发现任何东西有变化
Where is that thing, it's hard to tell.
我怎么才能找到这个识别器呢？
Well, there's two places you
好的，有两个地方你可以
can find that thing you just dropped.
找到你刚才放置的手势识别器
One is in the document outline.
一个是在 Document Outline 中
You see it right here?
你在这里看到了吗？
Pan Gesture Recognizer.
Pan Gesture Recognizer
Another one is, right at the top.
另外一个地方是，就在这个视图的顶部
If you look at the view controller right here, you'll
如果你在 Storyboard 中查看你的 View Controller，你会
see there's a Pan Gesture Recognizer right there.
看到这里有一个叫 Pan Gesture Recognizer 的东西
Okay. Now all you need to do
好的，现在你所要做的就是
to make this pan gesture recognizer be handled by your
让这个拖动手势识别器被你的控制器所处理
controller is Ctrl + drag.
利用 Control 键加拖动
So I'm holding down Ctrl and dragging in here, okay.
我这里按住我的 Control 键，并拖动到这里
Let go.
释放拖动
It's an action kind of like target action for
这是一个 Action，类似于按钮中的 Target Action
a button, but not quite exactly the same.
但不是完全相同
And I'm gonna call this change happiness cuz that's what
我把这个 Action 称之为 changeHappiness 因为
this pan gesture does.
这是这个拖动手势识别器所做的事情
Again, type I don't want to be any object.
再一次注意，这里的类型我不希望是 AnyObject
This is gonna be the type of the argument.
这里设置的是参数的类型
I want it to be Pan Gesture Recognizer.
我想要让我参数的类型是 UIPanGestureRecognizer
If you leave any object in there you'll have to be
如果你这里保留的是 AnyObject，那么
using as to turn it into a pan gesture recognizer so we can
你将要使用 as 将其类型转换为一个 UIPanGestureRecognizer 再使用它
use it, but obviously a lot easier to just click it here.
显然我这里设置好比较简单
The same as we had when we did button action.
这和我们处理按钮的时候是一样的
So it can connect, okay, here it is right here.
单击 Connect，好的，一个 Action 方法就建立好了
Let's go look at it.
让我们看看
Okay, change happiness.
changeHappiness
And now we just need to implement this one.
现在我们只需要实现这个方法即可
So, what do we need to do to change our happiness?
我们需要在 changeHappiness 中做什么呢？
Well the pan is moving up and down,
我们知道，这个拖动手势识别的是拖上拖下的操作
so I can get the coordinates of the pan in the face views
我可以获取到，在 faceView 中拖动时手指的坐标位置
coordinate system, but
在 faceView 的坐标系中
I really need to turn that into a happiness change in
但是，我真正需要的是将坐标的变换
some interpretations.
解释成一些其他的东西，其他可以导致我的小人脸部表情变化的东西
So again the controller is now interpreting what's
再一次，控制器现在承担了解释的操作
happening in the view for the model, so it's going in
为 Model 解释 View 目前正在发生什么
the opposite direction of where we went before.
是不是与之前的方向相反
And again, that's the controller's main job,
再次重申，这个才是控制器的主要任务
interpreting the model for the view and
为 View 去解释 Model，同时
the view input to modify the model.
接受 View 的输入来改变 Model
So how's this going to work?
这里怎么让我们的方法工作？
So again, I'm going to do sender.state = .changed.
我输入 if sender.state == .changed
I'm not going to do this because if I do this,
噢，我不打算这么做，因为如果我这么做的话
everyone out there is going to start doing the same thing.
你们每一个人也将会做同样的事情
So let's do a switch of this.
让我们使用一个 switch
I'm going to switch on the gestures, state.
输入 switch gesture.state
I'm going to handle the case where it ended and
在里面，我会处理 .Ended 这样的情况
I'm going to handle the case where it changed, okay.
同样我会处理 .Changed 这样的情况
And I'm just going to do them the same, so
这两个情况之下，我将使用同样的处理方法
I'll do this fall through like we did in the slides.
所以我将 .Ended 情况设置为 fallthrough，就在我们之前所做的那样
So, when this pan is changing or when the finger lifts up,
所以，当用户正在拖动，或者当他们的手指离开屏幕的时候
I'm going to try and change my happiness, okay.
我将尝试改变我的小人的 happiness，明白了吗？
So, first let's get the translation of the pan in
首先我们先在 faceView 的坐标系空间里
the face views coordinate system.
将这个 translation
And to do that I'm going to send a message to the sender,
这里我要做的就是，给 Sender 发送一个消息
you see sender right here?
你看到这里的 Sender 了吗？
That's the pan gesture recognizer that
这就是我们在这里
is being handled here.
处理的 UIPanGestureRecognizer
We call this gesture in the other one and
我们称之为 sender
a lot of people like to change this to gesture,
另外有些人习惯称之为 gesture
which I think is perfectly fine to want to do.
这里我认为没有任何问题
So I'm going to ask the gesture,
接下来，我将要让 gesture
tell me the translation in the face views coordinate system.
告诉我在 faceView 坐标系中的转换结果
So now I know how much it's moved in
那么现在我就知道拖动操作在
the face view coordinate system.
faceView 的坐标系系统中到底移动了多少位置
And so I'm going to let the happiness change, this is
接下来，我要让 happinessChange
the amount of change that's happening in my happiness.
变成我希望在 happiness 中变化的量
I could just have it be equal to translation.y, probably
我可以这里让它等于 translation.y
would wanna be -translation.y because up means happy and
但是我更希望让它等于 -translation.y，因为向上拖动表示开心
down means not happy.
向下拖动表示不开心
But that's going to change the happiness a lot with very
但是这里的问题时，一个很小的拖动就会极大地改变
small movements.
happiness 的值
So I don't really want that.
我不希望是这样的
So I really want to have, also it needs to be an int by
我真正希望的是，当然我希望它是一个整形的值
the way, so do that, because happiness is an int.
因为 happiness 本身是一个整形的值
I really want this changed last so
我真正希望的是，它的变化量不那么大
I'm going to actually divide this by a constant.
所以我会将 -translation.y 除以一个常量
So I'm going to create a constant here,
这里我将创建一个常量
Constants.HappinessGestureS- cale I'll call it.
称之为 Constants.HappinessGestureScale
And we'll go back up here and I'll do the private struct
我们回到上面，定义一个叫 Constants 的 private struct
constants, and this is a static let,
里面输入 static let
this thing which is a CG float.
这个常量应该是一个 CGFloat
Let's do four.
让我们设置为4
So for every four points we move,
那么，我们每拖动或移动4个像素点
we'll move our happiness by one.
我们会让我们 happiness 改变1
Then we could play with this constant.
我们可以尝试不同的值
That's part of the reason I'm putting it out in a constant.
这就是为什么我把它单独拿出来的一个原因
We could play with this number until we got the feel that we
我们可以不断尝试其他的值，直到
thought felt right for changing our happiness, okay.
我们觉得合适了
So we got our happiness changed.
现在，我们有了 happinessChange
So if the happiness change is not zero.
然后，如果 happinessChange 不是0的话
So if the happiness actually changed then I'm going to
那么我将改变我的 happiness
change my happiness, happiness += happinessChange.
happiness += happinessChange
I'm also going to do that reset thing.
接着我将做一些重置工作
So gesture.setTranslation(CGPoin-
gesture.setTranslation(CGPointZero,
tZero in my faceView.
inView: faceView)
I'm resetting it because I'm changing my happiness every
我重置它的原因是，当我每一次改变我的 happiness 的时候
time it changes, so I'm going to constantly be resetting it
我将持续重置它
so that it's incremental, okay.
以保证它是增量变化
And then of course we need to have the default case,
当然，我们需要 default 情况
which is going to be cancelled or failed or
比如说取消或者失败
began, and I'm just going to do nothing in that case.
或者是刚开始的情况，那么我将在 default 情况下不做任何操作
So any other state that gets thrown to me, I'll do nothing.
那么另外的状态触发了 changeHappiness 后，我将不做任何操作
So let's see if that works, let's run.
让我们看看是不是能够正常工作，让我们运行
Here we go, so now up is happier.
向上拖动，我们的小人看上去更开心了
Down is sad.
向下拖动，我们的小人看上去比较伤心
Up, good.
再向上，很好
And we can still do this.
当然我们还可以做缩放的操作
Okay, so these gestures, they don't look the same.
好的，所以这些手势，它们是不一样的
Okay, they don't start the same.
从根本上就不一样
This one's a two-finger one,
这一个是双指手势
okay, and this is a one-finger one.
这一个是单指手势
So the system can easily tell the difference between
系统可以轻易分辨出
which one is going on and IOS is very good at
到底是哪一种手势
telling the difference between different gestures starting.
iOS 尤其擅长这部分的东西
Okay? So everybody got that?
每个人都弄明白了吗？
So we did a lot of different kind of
我们在这里处理了不同种类的
gesture handling there.
手势
We added one in a storyboard.
我们学习了如何通过 Storyboard 添加一个手势
We added one in code.
也学习了如何通过代码来添加
We handled one in our controller.
我们在我们的控制器中处理了一个
We handled one in our face view.
另外一个在 faceView 里处理了
One is scaling and pinching, the other one was translation.
前者的的操作是处理尺寸缩放，后者是处理坐标系的变换
So hopefully between those two,
所以我希望你们通过这两个
you can look through that code and kinda get a good feel for
的代码，知道手势识别大致的一个处理流程
how the gestures go.
Okay, good, so we do have some time left.
好的，我们还剩下一些时间
I'm going to get started on the next topic here.
我将开始讲下一个话题
Before I do that, because I'm going to get interrupted in
在这之前，我想打断一下
the middle, let's talk quickly about what's coming up.
我要讲一下接下来的打算
So on Wednesday I'm going to continue the slides that I'm
周三我们会继续 Slide
going to start in a minute here.
我马上要讲的这个 Slide
About multiple MVCs and
这个 Slide 有关多个 MVC
then I'm gonna do a big demo creating multiple MVCs in
我将要演示一个大的 demo，
our happiness controller, okay.
在 happiness controller 中创建多个 MVC
And again, time permitting, at the end of Wednesday I'll do
如果时间允许，在周三课程最后我会讲
another topic view controller lifecycle.
另一个主题，即 view controller 生命周期
Friday, hopefully, it will have this instruments thing.
在周五，希望可以能够给大家讲一讲 instruments
And then next Monday I put auto layout question mark.
在下周一… 我在 auto layout 后放了一个问号
Because I was telling you I was going to
因为我曾经告诉你们我会很快讲 auto layout 的内容
do auto layout sooner but I keep putting it off.
但是总是推迟。
And I might put it off again, we'll see.
或许我会继续推迟，到时候就知道了。
But I won't be asking you in
但是我不会要求你们
your homework to do much sophisticated auto layout.
在课后花太多时间熟悉 auto layout 的内容。
So even it assignment three, there's very little.
所以尽管在它（auto layout）是第三次作业，但是也只是很少一部分内容。
Okay, so next topic, multiple MVCs.
好的，下一个主题，多重 MVC。
So you remember this picture, I hope.
我希望你还记得这张图
Which was at the of the MVC talk where I talked about how
在讲到 MVC 的最后，我讲了如果我们想
if we wanna build a big app,
构建一个大的应用，
we're gonna do it by putting multiple MVCs together, okay.
我们将要把多个 MVC 放在一起来实现它。
So we're gonna zoom in here and
将这幅图缩小
take a look at exactly how that's done.
看一看到底是怎么实现的。
Okay, how we're
我们怎么
gonna make multiple combine multiple MVC's.
将多个 MVC 联系到一起。
Okay.
So you see that MVC right there the purple one
看最上边紫色的这个 MVC
at the top, that's an MVC and you can
这是一个 MVC ，而且它（MVC）的 view
see that this view is actually made up of other MVC's.
实际上是由其它 MVC 组成的。
So iOS provides some controllers for
iOS 为 为一些 MVCs 中的 controllers 提供
MVCs that have other MVCs as their view.
了其它 MVCs 作为 controllers 的 view。
And the three we're gonna talk about today,
今天我们要讲到三个 controller,
by the way you can build your own.
BTW, 你可以创建自己的 controller。
I'm not gonna talk about that today.
今天我不会讲怎么自定义 controller
You can build your own controllers that have MVCs as
你可以自定义 controller ，并将 其它 MVC 作为 view
the view, but I'm gonna talk about the three that are
但是我今天要讲的三种 controller 是 iOS 内置的
provided in iOS which you're gonna be using in this class.
也是你们在这节课将要用到的。
Which is TabBarController SplitViewControllers and
这三个 controller 分别是 TabBarController SplitViewControllers
NavigationControllers, 'kay.
和 NavigationControllers。
So these are just controllers,
它们都是controller
they're subclasses of UIViewController.
是 UIViewcontroller 的子类。
And they draw a little bit in their view but
而且它们会在它们的 view 中绘制一些东西
then most of their view is what other MVC's draw, so
但是多数情况下，它们的 view 是其它 MVC 绘制的内容，
the MVCs are part of their views.
所以其它 MVC 只是这些 controller 视图的一部分。
So let's look at TabBarController,
看看 TabBarController
it's probably the simplest one of all these.
它可能是三个中最简单的
You've seen TabBarControllers,
你们已经见过 TabBarControllers,
you see it's got the four tabs along the bottom on this one.
这个 TabBarController 底部罗列了四个 tab。
This is the health app, I think.
我觉得这个一个健康类的应用。
And all that happens here is when you click one of those
当你点击底部四个 tab button
tab buttons at the bottom, the top gets replaced with an MVC.
中的一个，上面就会被一个新的 MVC 替换。
An entire MVC is controlling that top.
整个 MVC 控制上面的内容。
In this case, it's some sort of dashboard MVC or health
在本例中，这上面要展现的是一个 MVC 的 dashboard（仪表盘）
dashboard is being presented at the top, right here.
或是一个 健康的 dashboard（仪表盘）。
And the icon and
dashboard（仪表盘）下面的 icon（图标）以及
the title that goes along with the dashboard down there,
title（标题）
is actually gotten from the dashboard MVC.
实际上来自这个 dashboard （仪表盘）MVC。
In other words,
换句话说，icon 和 title
not a property you set on the UITabBarController MVC.
不是你在 UITabBarController MVC 中设置的 property（属性）。
You actually just have a property on
实际上在你的 dashboard MVC 中，
your dashboard MVC, it's called tabBarItem.
你仅有一个叫做 tabBarItem 的属性
And inside tabBarItem, if you go look it up in the doc,
在 tabBarItem 中， 如果你查找文档，
it's got things like title, icon, things that the tab bar
tabBarItem 中有 title（标题），icon（图标），等，这些东西
controller needs to put a nice tab on the bottom for
都是 tabBarController 需要的，用来为你的 dashboard底部
your dashboard MVC.
呈现一个适当的 tab。
So, as you can see, it's very object oriented, okay.
可以看到，这非常符合面向对象的思想。
Everything is contained in just this MVC.
所有的东西都在这个 MVC 中。
And so, if you press on a different tab,
如果你按下另一个 tab，
maybe the second tab, then this is a totally
比如第二个 tab，然后
different MVC that takes over the top of this screen.
一个完全不同的MVC占据了屏幕的顶部。
This would be Health Data MVC, and you can see that it's got
这是 Health Data MVC, 可以看到
a different icon and text down there, right?
它有一个不同的 icon 和 title 在它下面，对吧？
By the way, if there's too
顺便说下，如果底部罗列了
many tabs along the bottom there, I think you get five,
太多 tab，比如有5个tab，
if you go to six tabs then iOS will automatically let
如果你要六个 tab，那么iOS将会自动让
the user manage which ones he wants down there.
用户来决定他想要哪些tab。
It's pretty cool, okay.
相当 cool，对吧。
So you don't even have to and
你可以在下面放
you can put as many tabs you want.
任意多的 tab。
I don't really recommend more than five
但是，我建议不超过五个。
tabs here, by the way.
顺便一说。
For users it's like, what,
对于用户来说情况可能是：“ 什么？
I have to manage my tabs down there, I don't wanna do that.
我还得自己管理 tab，我可不想这么玛法 ”。
It's just that you're asking yours to do more stuff.
这是自己给自己找麻烦。
So hopefully you can fit it in five.
所以希望5个 tab 可以满足你的要求。
And so we have other MVCs as well.
我们也有其它 MVC
So there's the sources of health data,
这个是 health data（健康数据）的来源，
I guess, in your Medical ID tab.
在你的 Medical ID tab.
And so this is a very simple thing you can understand.
这些东西都很容易理解
You've got this UITabBarController,
你得到了这个 UITabBarController
it's a controller of an MVC.
它是一个 MVC 的 controller.
The view is the little tabs along the bottom that it's
它的（UITabBarController）的 view 是底部的它绘制的这些 tab
drawing and the MVC's on the top.
以及顶部的 MVC。
Everyone understand what I
大家都明白我说的吗？
mean now about an MVC whose view contains other MVC's?
关于一个 MVC 的 view 包含其它 MVC。
So let's look at another one that does that.
好的，一起看一下另一个 的 controller。
SplitViewController.
So, SplitViewController takes two MVCs, and
SplitViewController 包括两个 MVC，
it puts them side-by-side, okay.
并将它们并排放在一起。
It puts the one on the left,
它将一个放在左边。
kind of a well known width there.
似乎是一个熟知的宽度
But, you don't care what that width is because,
但是，你不必关心宽度是多少，
hopefully, you've got auto-layout, and so
你可以使用 auto-layout，
it could be any width you want, or
想让它多宽，
any height you want, like this.
想让它都高都可以，就像这样。
And then it puts another one on the right.
然后，它（UISplitViewController）将另一个 MVC 放在右边。
Now, we call the MVC on the left, the Master in
接下来，我们将左边的 MVC 叫做 split view 的 Master
the split view and we call the MVC on the right the Detail.
将右边的 MVC 叫做 Detail。
Now here I've got a calculator and a calculator graph.
目前我有一个计算器和一个计算器图表。
You assignment three is going to be to build this basically.
你们第三次作业基本上将要实现这个计算器。
It doesn't have to look exactly like this, okay.
你们的计算器不必和我的完全一样。
I've made a simple looking one here.
我只做了一个简单的外观。
But it could look very much like this.
但是你们的作业可能和我展示的样子差不了多少。
But you do have to use a SplitViewController.
但是你必须使用一个 SplitViewController。
So this is what it looks like.
现在它就是这个样子。
Now, this is only happening on an iPad.
当然，只有在 iPad 上才会这样。
Now, when we talk about auto layout,
当我们说到 auto layout，
we're going to start talking about size classes.
我们就要从 size classes 开始说起。
So, different devices have been grouped into
各种不同尺寸的 iOS 设备
size classes.
都被集成到了 size classes 中。
And the sizes basically are regular, so regular width and
size 通常为 regular，regular width 和 regular height
regular height or compact width and height.
或者 compact width， compact height。
So an iPhone, all the iPhones except for
对于 iPhone 来说，除了在
the iPhone 6+ in landscape,
landscape（横向模式）的 iPhone 6+，
are compact both vertically and horizontally, okay.
在水平方向和竖直方向都是 compact。
The iPad is regular width, okay.
iPad 是 regular width。
Now, that's of the whole device.
这就是整个设备。
But the MVC's inside also will have a certain size class.
但是设备里（iPad）的 MVC 同样有特定的 size class。
So this side by side business can only happen in
所以这样并排排列的 MVC 只能出现在
a device whose size class is regular width.
拥有 regular width 的 size class。
So that's the iPad in both landscape and portrait could
所有只有 iPad 在 landscape（横向模式）和 portrait（纵向模式）是 regular width，
be that, and the iPhone 6+ in landscape, okay.
iPhone 6+ 在 landscape（横向模式）下也是 regular width 。
So SplitView is only gonna do the side by
所以 SplitView 只能在这几种情况下并排放置。
side business there.
And if you rotate the iPad, then the Master disappears.
如果你旋转 iPad，Master 消失了。
But it can be swiped out.
但是可以将 Master 滑动唤出。
If you just swipe from the left, when you rotate the only
如果你从屏幕左边滑动，当 ipad 旋转时只有 Detail 视图，
ones there is the Detail, you don't see the Master.
看不到 Master。
But if you swipe out from the left,
但是如果你从左向右滑动，
then you get to see the Master as well.
你也可以看到 Master。
Again, side by side.
Master 和 Detail 又并排放在一起了。
Okay.
And if you touch the Detail, it'll make the Master go
如果你点击 Detail，会使 Master 返回消失
back away and then you can swipe it.
然后可以再次滑动唤出。
So you can bring the Master out or not, okay.
所以你可以决定是否唤出 Maser。
That make sense?
懂了吗？
So that's the SplitViewController,
以上是 SplitViewController
kind of how it's arranged.
以及它怎么排列。
But most importantly, I want you to understand that again,
最重要的是，我想让你们再次理解
it's two MVCs that are the view.
这两个 MVC 是 view。
Now the SplitView draws nothing in its view,
SplitView 并没有在它的 view 中绘制任何内容，
except for maybe that vertical separator line.
可能除了竖直的分界线。
Okay, there's a vertical separator line.
这条竖直的分界线。
That's probably drawn by the SplitViewController, but
可能是 SplitViewController 绘制的，
otherwise it's only drawing  whatever the MVCs draw.
但是，他只展示了 MVC 绘制的内容
So it doesn't even have any drawing on
所以，它甚至不像 tabBarViewController 那样
the bottom like the TabBar has.
绘制底部的 tabBar。
Okay?
So the next thing I'm going to talk about, and
下面我要讲到的，
we're going to start this next time,
以及我们要再下一节课继续讲的是
is NavigationController, which is a very powerful one.
NavigationController， 这是一个功能强大的 controller。
It draws at the top a little title and
它在顶部绘制小的 title 和其他东西，
some things, it can draw even around the bottom.
它甚至可以在底部周围绘制内容。
And then it can display any number of MVCs.
还有，它可以展示任意多的 MVC。
Okay, so we'll pick up the NavigationController next time
好的，下节课我们将要学习 NavigationController
and in the meantime if you have any questions,
如果你有任何问题要问，
I'll be here as usual.
我会像往常一样在这里解答。
>> For more, please visit us at www.stanford.edu
>> 登录 www.stanford.edu 获取更多内容。